<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>IF-Review</title>
    <subtitle>An online magazine for in-depth reviews of interactive fiction.</subtitle>
    <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2001-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>A Review of Stranded</title>
        <author><name>Dan Shiovitz</name></author>
        <published>2001-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010824/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010824/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;gametext rounded&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Rest Room&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;P&gt;
This is the dingy but clean bathroom of the Odduck Diner. It has the
typical fixtures: sink, mirror and toilet. A door to the south leads
to the diner. (Type &#x27;&lt;B&gt;help&lt;&#x2F;B&gt;&#x27; and press &lt;B&gt;ENTER&lt;&#x2F;B&gt;). 
&lt;&#x2F;P&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt;FLUSH TOILET&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
Woosh!
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m not a picky guy. Basically, as long as a game that has a toilet supports
&#x27;flush toilet&#x27;, I&#x27;m happy. It&#x27;s good that I have these simple tastes because
&lt;em&gt;Stranded&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; doesn&#x27;t really offer anything complex.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say it&#x27;s a bad game. But, well,
&lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.u.arizona.edu&#x2F;%7Ebayers&#x2F;&quot;&gt;the author&#x27;s website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; describes it as &amp;quot;an
educational interactive fiction game&amp;quot;. For some reason, games which are
marketed as &amp;quot;educational&amp;quot; always seem to be targeted precisely at a particular
age level, and &amp;quot;education&amp;quot; always seems to imply &amp;quot;in math&amp;quot;. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stranded&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; follows the model pretty closely, in the sense that it&#x27;s easy to get
started with (with lots of helpful tips on how to play IF scattered through the
text, as seen in the room description above), has a bunch of brightly-colored
pictures (illustrated by Igor Revyakin, who should be commended for striking
just the right note with his drawings), and has little puzzles stuck in that
don&#x27;t feel quite natural (&amp;quot;This ceiling is in need of painting. It is covered
in square tiles. The tiles make up a pattern like a checker board. Each tile
measures one foot by one foot. Counting from east to west, there are ten tiles
in a row. Counting from north to south, there are ten tiles in a row as well.&amp;quot;
— and later on, of course, you have to figure out how much paint to buy).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, let me put the educational issue aside for the moment and talk about
this purely from an IF perspective. &lt;em&gt;Stranded&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; does a number of things right.
Besides the aforementioned good use of graphics, Bayers does a good job of
setting up a small town with a variety of interesting people. The people are
suspiciously ethnically diverse, and it&#x27;s not really clear where everyone&#x27;s
houses are and so on, but these are pretty excusable given the genre (i.e.,
wandering around a small town solving puzzles). The game sets a consistent tone
in the writing and character depictions, which is harder for a puzzle game than
you might think, and there are no weird anachronisms. At the same time, it&#x27;s
not a bland world: there are enough oddball things (the ducks, the mysterious
Nookums) to make it unique and memorable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The puzzles, unfortunately, could use some work. Some of them (the
ceiling-painting, the rake retrieval) are ones that you could reasonably
stumble across and figure out what you&#x27;re supposed to do; for others, like the
car wash and the cake, it seems like it&#x27;d be hard to figure out that they
exist, let alone how to solve them. Then there&#x27;s a few (eg, raking the leaves)
where you find the puzzle, and there are a bunch of plausible ways to solve it,
and exactly one of them has been implemented and there&#x27;s an uncommunicative
failure message if you try anything else. This is just poor game design,
regardless of the target age range, and shows the author should have done more
beta-testing. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People have varying degrees of pedanticism when it comes to analyzing other
people&#x27;s writing. I&#x27;m, relatively speaking, pretty low-key about this sort of
thing. But particularly in a game supposed to be educational, even I am
somewhat jarred when I see things like &amp;quot;Wearing a baseball hat and dark
glasses, you see groundskeeper Earl.&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Don&#x27;t let the educational part
through you&amp;quot;. Then there are occasional other smaller errors of the sort that
(again) should have been caught by beta-testing, &amp;quot;Next to the door, are is the
number &#x27;46&#x27;.&amp;quot; The writing in this game isn&#x27;t made unreadable by these errors,
but they are distracting for older players and (I would think) confusing for
younger ones. Bayers would have benefitted from more extensive beta-testing
and&#x2F;or a look-over by somebody with a better ear for grammar.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I feel as though I should talk about educational games more generally.
There is the unspoken theory in some circles that kids don&#x27;t enjoy learning
things, that they need to somehow be tricked into education or they will just
sit there aimlessly. And the result is games marketed as &amp;quot;educational&amp;quot;, when
what this really means is that they&#x27;re &lt;em&gt;less educational&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; than most games (for
adults), and hence kids are supposed to, I guess, accept them more easily. But
this is stupid and condescending. If you really want to educate the kid, give
them something really solid and well-crafted like, say, &lt;em&gt;So Far&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, and let them
play that. Sure, they won&#x27;t get 50% of the puzzles or 95% of the subtext, but
they&#x27;ll get enough to be interested. And every part they see will be excellent,
and when they come back to it later there&#x27;ll be more excellent stuff to get
then.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t mean to give the impression &lt;em&gt;Stranded&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is unplayably horrible or
anything like that. I spent an evening on it, used hints in a few places, and
it was perky and fun. But it&#x27;s not a piece of IF that I&#x27;m going to be
remembering a year from now, and particularly for an educational game it could
have used more beta-testing, both in writing and in game design.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you want to know how it ends, you&#x27;ll have to play the game.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Taking A Swing</title>
        <author><name>Emily Short</name></author>
        <published>2001-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010810/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010810/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The recent release of Sean Barrett&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;The Weapon&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; suggested the polish and care
of a major production, accompanied as it was by a virtual-feelie html file.
I&#x27;ve been arguing for more such feelies; they&#x27;re a way to add color to a game
and provide background, and they set off the large-scale games from their
smaller and more casual counterparts. In what follows I shall discuss both the
game and its virtual packaging.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s the good news: the game is exceptionally polished, technically, and the
feelies are well suited to it. If you are one of those who have been clamoring
for more long games sized large enough to be unsuitable for the competition,
however, you&#x27;re out of luck. It took me probably less than 45 minutes, in two
sessions, to play it; it would have taken longer if there had not been a hint
system, to which I had frequent recourse. (It seems that when there is a hint
system, I always use it. This probably says more about me than it does about
the games to which the hints belong, but it also suggests, perhaps, why people
haven&#x27;t been talking about &lt;em&gt;The Weapon&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; much on rgif; there is nothing to get
hung up on, since if you want you can get a full walkthrough out of the game,
and there are no bugs that I was able to find.) Even so I doubt it could have
run more than the regulation two hours, and if it had it would have been
because I&#x27;d gotten massively stuck.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Weapon&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is set in a distant, chilly future, as the feelies will instantly
reveal. The newspaper articles (or html equivalent) suggest troubled times for
Earth, and interactions with two alien species; they are also larded with
references and vocabulary that don&#x27;t make any sense at all, which, I presume,
is an attempt to reflect a future time in which new jargons and concerns have
sprung up of which we can anticipate nothing. Considering how very &lt;em&gt;far&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in the
future this seems to be set, it seems that this doesn&#x27;t go far enough — I
have a hard time believing that we will still have anything like newspapers,
let alone use anything like English, if the human race is still around in
33,000 years. But some concessions must be made to the comprehensibility, and
it is an effective way to remind us that the distant future will be a strange
place. (Though I&#x27;d love to see what the feelies would look like for &lt;em&gt;Lighan ses
Lion&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disappointments in the feelie department are, first, that I found a few
passages unconvincing as editorial journalism, and, second, that the page
abounds with what would appear to be links, but they can&#x27;t be clicked upon.
This is hardly surprising considering that to implement an &lt;em&gt;entire&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; future
newspaper as a game feelie would be a task of wearisome magnitude, providing
diminishing returns in terms of enjoyability. But, but, but, I hasten to say, I
would rather have seen these as mere references to other pages I didn&#x27;t possess
than as bright-blue-underlined-html-style things that just begged to be clicked
on and then did nothing. This is the equivalent of examining something
mentioned in a game and getting &amp;quot;You can see no such thing.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the same, the feelies are a useful and perhaps even necessary background to
understanding what is going on in the game, and they are pleasantly
illustrated. The sense of whimsy of Infocom feelies is absent; perhaps it would
be out of place, though I would point out that Infocom&#x27;s feelies tended to be
entertaining even when the games themselves were somewhat serious. Or perhaps I
just derived too much excitable dread from wondering what would happen if I
swallowed the pill samples from &lt;em&gt;Deadline&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game itself bears out the coldness and strangeness of the feelie page. Your
player character obviously possesses considerable and important knowledge about
what is going on, but you as the player have no access to his emotions; he sees
and understands much, but the descriptions are abstractly scientific and
mathematical, with only the twinges of an underlying bias. Nonetheless, one
begins to assemble a picture of what is going on — which is good,
considering how much you are required, at the beginning, to act in a vacuum of
understanding.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This vacuum, combined with the iced precision of the object descriptions and
the non-interactivity of the NPC (about which more in a moment), almost caused
me to give up on this game in the early stages. There is plenty to look at, but
it is not always that exciting to see; examination of each object and each
component of an object becomes more a discipline than a pleasure. I always know
that I&#x27;ve lost immersion when I pick out the nouns from a paragraph and type
&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;X THING&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;X NEXT THING&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;X LAST THING&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; in quick succession without
bothering to read the answers in between. It&#x27;s a kind of trick to make sure
that I don&#x27;t miss or forget anything, and I can catch up and read the
descriptions that result afterwards. But it also tends to point to a distrust
of the game as narrative, or a loss of engagement. I was looking at objects in
order to garner game-progressing information, not because I was inherently
interested in what I would see thereby.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Being Andrew Plotkin&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; has, as a humorous effect, a scene in which you are
seeing objects through zarf&#x27;s head, and they are given with exact measurements
of sizes and shapes. But the funny thing is that precision in zarf&#x27;s own games
tends to be in aid of, rather than a substitute for, striking imagery. &lt;em&gt;The
Weapon&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; game had a sterility, a frosty quality, and something approaching
emotional numbness on the PC&#x27;s part. It is the antithesis of wonder.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason I harp so much on this problem of examining is that it constitutes
most of what you have to do in the game. There are indeed puzzles, but most of
the puzzles consist of using the behavior of items that you have examined.
Usually fairly directly. I know I have come out in favor of something very like
this in the case of, say, &lt;em&gt;Spider and Web&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, and that a similar complaint could
be leveled at my own &lt;em&gt;Metamorphoses&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, but I think there&#x27;s a fundamental
difference between examining something to find out what it will do and
examining something to be told what you should use it for. Descriptions in &lt;em&gt;The
Weapon&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; seem to be all hint and puzzle component &lt;em&gt;and nothing else&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. This might
be workable in a game with a clearer sense of plot (for the player, I mean; the
author has a very good sense of the plot of his game, and it is a compact piece
reminiscent of an old-series &lt;em&gt;Twilight Zone&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; episode, featuring no deviations
or variations.) But for the player, it&#x27;s not clear why he&#x27;s doing what he&#x27;s
doing, at first, so there&#x27;s no pay-off at the story level for doing things. The
problem is that what the player has to do in the short term isn&#x27;t especially
fun (no toy value) and one starts with no sense of the overall procedure or
plot (no story value).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other irritation (as I mentioned above) is the problem with the NPC. Sean
Barrett has relied, here, on a conversation system based on &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;TALK&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; (a la
&lt;em&gt;Kaged&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Masquerade&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;), combined with more specific commands like &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;ASK PERSON FOR THING&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. There is no way to inquire about topics of the player&#x27;s
choice, either through menus or with ASK&#x2F;TELL. The monolithic &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;TALK&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; worked
(for me, at least) in the plot-heavy games referred to above: not only do you
have a pretty good sense of who your character is and why that person acts a
certain way, but you can also guess, within reason, what is likely to come out
of the character&#x27;s mouth if you do choose to use talk.  Moreover, the momentum
of both stories is sufficient to make it desirable to move forward through
conversation scenes according to a script.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here there wasn&#x27;t a script so much as a few rather dull exchanges, most
intended to shed light on the puzzles at hand. I had lots of questions and
things I wanted to bring up, but I wasn&#x27;t allowed to.  The fact that I wasn&#x27;t
allowed to itself probably has something to do with the shape of the story, but
it was still kind of irritating. My PC only speaks when spoken to and never
seems to generate particularly lengthy or interesting replies. The NPC speaking
to him in only slightly better in this regard; she reveals her attitude towards
the PC and her goals in game terms with an iron straight-forwardness that
reveals no particular of character.  There&#x27;s not much by way of tension, or
emotion, or flashes of humor however dark. And — and I can&#x27;t tell you why
this bothered me so much — she tends not to reply to what &lt;em&gt;I&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; say until a
turn after I said it. So some of the exchanges looked like this: &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;TALK&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.
&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;WAIT&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;TALK&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;WAIT&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would have forgiven that if the conversation itself had been more
interesting, however. I &lt;em&gt;believed&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in the existence of some kind of
relationship between the protagonist and his interrogator in &lt;em&gt;Spider and Web&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
(to which this game has certain distinct similarities of approach). Limited as
that interaction was, I felt the emotional content of it. Here there are hints
of some kind of history between the PC and the NPC, enough to provide the
beginnings of an interesting conversation, but that goes by the wayside. In
fact, come to think of it, if I wrote a game like this I would have them
talking constantly, the conversation not a mere functional backdrop to what is
happening but an important and integral part of the story.  Instead —
silence, or extreme stiltedness. And my disappointment here is not the
disappointment of an NPC fanatic but of a person forced to stare off in the
other direction while a fireworks display occurs. I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; there is the
material for a very striking story here. It&#x27;s just not the one that gets told.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can mentally hear the author&#x27;s response now: That Was Intentional.  Yes,
there may be an in-game reason for these things, just as there is an in-game
reason for the obscurity and peculiarity of certain works by Mr. Plotkin. But
the point is that you cannot let the service of an in-game goal make the game
itself unrewarding to play in the short term, or people will quit. I did quit,
but then I found myself wanting so badly to explain what I thought was wrong
with the game that I had to go finish it anyway. You can consider this, if you
like, a backhanded compliment; usually if I don&#x27;t like a game I don&#x27;t bother to
review it, and finish it rarely unless it is quite easy or short. But there was
considerable purpose and skill in this particular effort. It accomplishes some
complicated tasks of parsing and object interaction creditably, is thoroughly
implemented within its scope (ie, that everything should be examinable), and
showed, as I said, no signs of bugginess that I could find.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bottom line: at some level flawless, but also without the passion for its
characters, the sense of wonder in its environment, or the wacky humor that
distinguish my favorite games. A careful execution of its concept, but not one
that elicited much of a response from me, other than a vague curiosity to see
whether my hunch about where it was all going was correct. (Answer: yes.) There
were several puzzles whose solutions I would have been unlikely to guess on my
own, even considering the hint-filled nature of the descriptions, but that&#x27;s
okay, since there are also hint-filled menus. I&#x27;d say, I suppose, that it
succeeds quite well as a piece of programming, and that where it falls down is
in the writing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Have Psychosis, Will Travel</title>
        <author><name>Sam Kabo Ashwell</name></author>
        <published>2001-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010803/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010803/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(bigtime spoilers)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m often amazed at the quality of writing within the IF community, as
contrasted to the other internet-based writing communities. Perhaps it&#x27;s
because the process of coding requires a certain amount of persistence; perhaps
the time required to code everything allows writers more time in which to
critically edit their prose; undoubtedly the betatesting process improves the
overall standard of writing. Unfortunately, none of these apply when the piece
in question happens to be a transcript. Maybe it&#x27;s because the community&#x27;s
insularity scares the dull elves off... but anyway, the review.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read &lt;em&gt;Time Bastard&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; last of all the walkthroughcomp entries, by chance as much
as anything. Having seen the other entries, I wasn&#x27;t expecting wonders. The
first paragraph, therefore, blew me away: here, I realised, is some great
writing. Maybe it&#x27;s because I&#x27;m at that stage in my mental development where a)
antiestablishment rants = the pinnacle of morality, b) revolting = funny, and
c) packed with references = sophistication but, nonetheless, I was surprised at
how little reaction to it there was. The reason is, most probably, the fact
that it&#x27;s just a transcript.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The characterisation is excellent, with regard to both the protagonist and of
most of the other NPCs. In fact, it&#x27;s far and away the strong point of the
piece.  Now, in a character, I like flaws. A character without flaws is dull,
boring, and devoid of personality. Vincent Dobbs, the eponymous &lt;em&gt;Time Bastard&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;,
appears to be entirely composed of character flaws. He considers dried human
skin as a writing material &#x27;a neat effect&#x27;, hurls his own phlegm to solve
puzzles, and hands his friends napalm on the pretext that it&#x27;s Turkish Delight.
In short, he is a self-admitted criminally insane sociopath. Naturally, this
doesn&#x27;t make him any the less endearing; the best comic characters are the evil
ones; Dobbs would be the best PC of the year if he had actually been coded.
(Given what he actually is, this is just a little ironic). To add to the
characterisation, everything is delivered in the irreverent style of the PC,
usually amused (alternating with bipolar rapidity between laconic and
exuberant) but occasionally bubbling over into chain-reaction rage, and
occasionally (heaven forbid!) even quasi-seriousness. Given the second-person
perspective of the vast majority of IF, the definition of the PC by his
description of his environment is a largely underused technique, especially to
the extent to which it is taken by &lt;em&gt;Time Bastard&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;; there is not a puzzle
(except, perhaps, in the final scene) that&#x27;s resolved without, er... the phrase
&#x27;hilarity ensues&#x27; can actually be used with genuine meaning here. The humour,
however dark it gets, is light-hearted in the most inappropriate contexts (see
&#x27;those kyoot Chinese kids they got working down in the Hazardous Materials
refinery&#x27;); Vincent, in short, completely imposes himself upon the story at
every level.  And a good thing too.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the NPCs, I particularly loved Abdul. Much of the NPCs&#x27; actions reflect
as much on the protagonist as on themselves, and there are some excellent
touches here: for example, Abdul is reluctant to eat half of a &#x27;undulating cube
of living unpleasantness&#x27; offered to him by Vincent, on the principle that it
might be something unpleasant again, but on realising that it&#x27;s merely the
remnants of a tentacled experiment in occult eugenics, that only a second ago
was screeching at him from the ceiling, his response is &amp;quot;Ooo!  Calamari!&amp;quot;
Essentially, Abdul is just Vincent with a superiority complex and a reverence
of Cthulhu. He appears, unlike Dobbs, to know what he&#x27;s doing (this is
undermined later on): this is pretty essential, since Abdul initiates most of
the plot developments (one feels Vincent, left to his own devices, would never
have done anything but hit people). Abdul&#x27;s more remote bastardliness gives a
different comic perspective on the Time Bastard theme; his brand of insanity is
contrasted nicely with Vincent&#x27;s, even when he&#x27;s only demonstrating the finer
details of Tourette&#x27;s in the background.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that the main strength of the piece lies in well-developed unpleasant
characters, it comes as a strong and ironic contrast that the, er, villain is
so completely tedious. Abdul and Vincent may be disgusting, but Purity is far
worse: she&#x27;s bland (and intentionally so). Not only does she appear to be a
graduate from the So, Mr Bond College of Unbelievable Bad Guys, (tell your
enemies the intimate details of your evil masterplan, devise intricately
horrible fates for them, let them escape) but she has no taste at all:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gametext rounded&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Eww, they&#x27;re all sappy Larry Elmore-eque paintings of dragons!  You can 
already feel your gorge beginning to rise.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purity follows your gaze.  &quot;I like dragons.&quot; she informs you coldly.&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must destroy this woman as soon as humanly possible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a symbol of homogenised corporate culture and a clichéd authority
figure, she forms the ideal foil to Vincent; so much so that it&#x27;s a little
unbelievable that the latter would be able to divert himself to puzzle-solving
in her presence instead of attempting grievous bodily harm. (The general
anti-authority theme is well developed and, though parodied by exaggeration as
often as anything else in the piece (see the It&#x27;s Long Overdue rant) gives an
impression of being essentially heartfelt). Apart from her role as a bad-guy
parody, the humour fades and the tone becomes more serious as she becomes more
prominent; Dobbs&#x27; previously explosive anti-authoritarian tone becomes almost
subdued, which forms the dual role of allowing critical information to be
imparted to the reader in a vaguely serious tone, and of developing a great
deal of resentment: we want our interesting psycho back! What&#x27;s this tedious
apricot woman doing dominating the narrative and making the prose all
pedestrian? Where&#x27;s the mucus?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic plot, in Matt&#x27;s own words, is Asshole Running Amok Through Time; this
theme seems to be both separate from and (initially) stronger than the frame
story and the plot; for a linear game, &lt;em&gt;Time Bastard&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; initially seems almost
plotless. In fact, it seems to subvert all pretence of the game making sense to
the development of the Bastard through Time idea; since it&#x27;s basically an
intriguing idea, it carries it off for long enough to keep the reader&#x27;s
attention to the final scene (though whether it could carry this off as
walkthroughless IF is questionable; for example, in the penultimate Cromwell
scene, not the strongest of the piece, the interest wanes; &lt;em&gt;Time Bastard&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is
essentially a rapid series of very powerful hooks, and the Cromwell scene
doesn&#x27;t have any).  Rather than using the walkthroughcomp restraints as a
starting point, the game feels as if the author took an idea and then hammered
it into shape around the walkthrough. This turns out to be more or less the
case; Matt says that the idea&#x27;s about six years old.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot structure works well, although you don&#x27;t notice this until you&#x27;ve
re-read it at least once, and it leaves most of the details for the reader to
work out. The final resolution puts into context all the miscellaneous
unexplained weirdness and seeming irrationality of earlier scenes, and to a
large extent justifies it; re-reading and explaining events in the light of the
ending is as much fun as reading it for the first time. In the light of the
ending, things which at first appeared to be simply jokes on the nature of
parser interaction, on the confines of the walkthroughcomp, and at the expense
of IF generally can be interpreted as plot hints, and things which initially
seemed completely pointless or irrational turn out to be jokes on the
walkthroughcomp confines. Since &lt;em&gt;Time Bastard&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; doesn&#x27;t go out of its way to explain its
every last detail, I found myself going through the piece with a fine-toothed
comb and working out retrospective rationalisations. (A good technique; if you
can get your readers cross-examining your writing, everything in that writing
grows in significance). It even, potentially, explains why hard-man psychopath
Dobbs is so intimately familiar with the details of geek subjects (IF, RPGs,
use of the phrase w00t).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the sort of IF in which you don&#x27;t know why you&#x27;re trying to solve
a puzzle until you&#x27;ve solved it, and possibly a couple more puzzles down the
line. (I&#x27;m thinking of the Gold Boat puzzle in &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ifwiki.org&#x2F;index.php&#x2F;Heroine%27s_Mantle&quot;&gt;Heroine&#x27;s
Mantle&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; here). Time Bastard
is very much that sort of IF, but constantly refers to the fact that this is
the case (see the unreservedly superb Treasure Frenzy! conversation; initially,
this appears to be solely genre satire (and there&#x27;s plenty in here that was
probably intended only as genre parody) but this is rationalised by the ending.
The plot, which up until the ending (and second reading) strikes one as a weak
frame for a lot of injokes, character development and comp restraints, is
suddenly justified in its own right; this sleight of hand gives it perhaps more
apparent weight than it deserves in its own right. Another very nice technique,
and the appreciation of good technique always adds to the enjoyment of a piece.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If &lt;em&gt;Time Bastard&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; had been a fully-coded game, I would have said it had a good
level of verbosity; since it&#x27;s a transcript, this would have been easier to
achieve, and had it been actually interactive and without walkthrough, several
commands (especially towards the end) would have been all but impossible to
complete, but nonetheless: this is the density and quality of writing that
makes the difference between text-based adventure and interactive literature.
The same argument and qualifiers apply to the game&#x27;s (?) length. Similarly,
it&#x27;s been pointed out that it had something of an advantage over the other
transcript &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ifwiki.org&#x2F;index.php&#x2F;WalkthroughComp&quot;&gt;walkthroughcomp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
entrants in that it makes abundant use of non-essential commands which are, in
fact, essential to have any idea about what&#x27;s going on, if not to actually
complete the game it represents. It&#x27;s a reasonable point, but can&#x27;t really
detract from &lt;em&gt;Time Bastard&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&#x27;s value as a piece in its own right.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Time Bastard&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is just a little bit injokey. If you don&#x27;t follow
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;groups.google.com&#x2F;g&#x2F;rec.arts.int-fiction&quot;&gt;rec.arts.int-fiction&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; flame
wars, one scene in particular makes no sense at all, but is hilarious
otherwise. There are throwaway and considerably-less-than-throwaway references
to a host of other works of IF, which, are, as injokes tend to be, amusing if
you get &#x27;em and confusing if you don&#x27;t. Apart from that, it draws heavily
(again, with knowing amusement) on the Cthulhu genre and on The Matrix. (Except
that it takes steps the Matrix was too chicken to make; for example, the
protagonist is &lt;em&gt;part&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of nTopia rather than a human trapped in it, and the lead
villain is much more closely identified with corporate megalomania and
intrinsic human evil). And, yes, apparently that title is a corruption of the
Terry Gilliam vehicle Time Bandits. As heavily and frequently as &lt;em&gt;Time Bastard&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
draws on genre and even cliché, it always does so, as with everything
else, in gleefully self-aware style; the Pretentious Nazi Occultist Literature
section is perhaps the most obvious example.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Time Bastard&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is well-written, acutely self-aware, and so funny that it made me laugh out
loud at least once; it&#x27;s a demonstration of what a well-conceived comp can
achieve, an example of how very raw good ideas can be nailed down to some sort
of structure, and extremely enjoyable to read. In short, in my humble opinion,
this would be an excellent example of how IF should be done, if it were
actually IF. Curse.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who&#x27;s_y0ur_d4ddy, indeed. If this doesn&#x27;t get turned into full-blown IF, Matt
had better be prepared to be woken up one morning by the Yith breaking down his
door.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>First Reviews First</title>
        <author><name>Emily Short</name></author>
        <published>2001-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010727/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010727/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;First Things First&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is J. Robinson Wheeler&#x27;s newly-released but
long-in-development TADS game.  He warns in the documentation for it that it is
unlike much of his other work: after &lt;em&gt;Being Andrew Plotkin&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;The Kissing
Bandit&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, it&#x27;s startlingly broad in design.  And puzzle-oriented.  And a
time-travel story.  We&#x27;ve seen time travel in IF before, as a major feature
(&lt;em&gt;Jigsaw&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;) or as a puzzle set in a larger game (two Infocom games come to
mind), but I don&#x27;t believe I have encountered any in which the time travel
implications are so extensively implemented.  In &lt;em&gt;Jigsaw&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, one either leaves a
time period in an acceptable state or one doesn&#x27;t, and failing to do so doesn&#x27;t
allow you to glimpse the alternate realities that resulted in any detail.
FTF&#x27;s scope is more limited — a handful of locations, a few characters
one knows personally rather than the whole world — but one can travel
freely to and fro, making modifications and then viewing their effects.  An
ambitious scheme, and it is easy to see why such a game would have taken a long
time to develop and then (my mind cringes to think about it) beta-test.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FTF is considerably larger than your average game these days (since, as noted,
most of recent releases seem to be roughly competition sized.)  Not as
fiendishly difficult and long to play as something like Heroine&#x27;s Mantle, but
it still took me numerous hours, including staying up until dawn once and then
a couple of further playings to check out avenues I&#x27;d failed to explore.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It begins as an old-school sort of game, as the author freely admits and as is
evident from the first few moves.  There&#x27;s lots of scenery that can&#x27;t be used
or interacted with.  There&#x27;s an inventory limit, and limits to container
holdings, but these limits are the frustrating sort that don&#x27;t emulate any
feature of real life as I understand it: you can scrabble up the side of a
house with your hands completely loaded.  (No, I don&#x27;t mind this, because it
facilitates game play; I just find it odd that, given that I can do that, I
can&#x27;t also carry a bazillion objects around in other circumstances.)  A tightly
wedged drainpipe is capable of containing large objects.  Descriptions, at
least in the early part of the game, sometimes fail to change when they ought
to; you get &#x27;you finally step into {$place}&#x27; every time you go to a certain
location, for instance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early NPC characterization takes the form of one-line answers to keywords, and
then randomized actions.  There are points where you are surrounded by people,
milling around and doing things, but none of them is &#x27;important&#x27;: you can&#x27;t
look at them or address them or interact with them in any way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gameplay is similarly old-school, in that it consists of solving assorted
puzzles for the sake of solving them, using some often widely distributed and
peculiar components.  There are hints about what to do, granted; some of them
are rather broadly placed.  There are also moments where it isn&#x27;t clear whether
you&#x27;ve just lost your chance of victory or merely had something made less
convenient.  At several such points it seemed that it would have been useful to
have a &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;WINNABLE&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; command, to find out whether I had really just ruined
everything or whether I had merely placed it into a state from which I would be
able to rescue myself again later.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What else does an old-school game require?  Well, easter eggs, of course:
check.  And some in-jokes: check.  References to old Implementors, to classic
IF such as &lt;em&gt;Curses&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, to popular ifMUD sayings, sprinkle themselves about in
such a way as to almost-but-not-completely blend into the background.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, though the puzzles and some of the implementation date from a less
enlightened age, the archaic features are treated with a mocking, retrospective
humor.  You have to use &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;SEARCH&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; sometimes.  Sometimes you have to use it a
lot.  I&#x27;m just warning you now because I thought this was one of the most
potentially annoying aspects of the game, but it was also hilarious.
&amp;quot;Deprecated,&amp;quot; says Rob about some of the puzzles.  Here I am deprecating them,
right on schedule.  But they are so self-conscious, so exuberant in their
old-schoolness, that they were fun anyway.  Paradox? Maybe.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Puzzly though the game is, I was able to solve the whole thing without
resorting to external walkthroughs or hints, which is something I almost never
do.  I had to ask someone after the fact for some information since I won with
less than the optimal number of points, but the fact that I got that far at
all is a testament to the fact that the game is designed, if not
forgivingly, at least with an eye to being comprehensible.  There are many
points at which you can lock yourself out of victory.  On the other hand,
there were few puzzles that left me scratching my head and wondering how I
was supposed to have read the author&#x27;s mind.  The game is also developed to
provide hints; not only can you ask NPCs about topics and get useful
nudges, but they will even occasionally volunteer things unsolicited about
problems that you&#x27;ve been bashing your head against.  The realism of this
effect may vary, but as a piece of game design it&#x27;s excellent, a sort of
in-game adaptive hint system woven into the story.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the game presents itself as an old-school puzzle romp with a touch of wry
self-mockery...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...only, somewhere along the line, a plot begins to coalesce around you, and
themes emerge.  The NPCs cease to be just means to an end and become the end in
themselves.  The decisions that you have made blithely in pursuit of the game&#x27;s
agenda begin to take on deeper significance, as their effects ripple through
time.  To say too much about this would be to give the game away, but FTF is
about more than it initially appears to be; the change of perspective is itself
part of the story.  Classic old-school IF posits an anonymous adventurer with a
casually egotistical view of the world: everything is, obviously, there for the
taking, and one does what suits one&#x27;s own immediate ends, without qualm,
because the player, of course, knows that the universe has indeed been arranged
for the player-character&#x27;s use.  Not convenience, exactly; if it were arranged
for his convenience there wouldn&#x27;t be so many problems about lamp-oil and
twisty passages.  But there&#x27;s nothing wrong with taking what you can
use and putting it to whatever purpose you desire.  One of the curious
things about this game is that it progresses into its more modern,
thoughtful stages, it also becomes less about the player character per
se, who remains essentially a cipher in terms of personality, and more
about the NPCs.  Somewhere along the line the player character must
begin to act as though he has a conscience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How well the plot works for you may vary from person to person.  There were
aspects of it that did not wholly satisfy me, despite the fascinating
transition in the form of the game.  One of the necessities, perhaps, of
plot-heavy design is that it tends to become railroaded, and the moments where
the most is happening are also the ones where the player has the least control.
There may not be any easy ways around that problem, but I found myself, at
certain points, to be no more than a spectator in the evolution of someone
else&#x27;s life.  Or of my own: it&#x27;s evident that my character does, or has done,
or will do (figure out the temporality yourself) some interesting things,
but at the moment I barely understand them and have little to do with them:
there&#x27;s an element of faith in the preparation for events yet to come.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not true of all aspects of the game, however.  There is one part of the
plot that you must journey through, in prescribed fashion, to arrive at
victory.  But there is another part that is wholly optional, and depends upon
your personal compassion and determination; it reminded me of the optional
rescue of a certain creature in &lt;em&gt;Worlds Apart&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, but whereas I didn&#x27;t find
myself motivated to figure out the puzzle in that case, here I was sufficiently
bothered by failure that I replayed the game until I got a solution that
pleased me.  I don&#x27;t know what to call this kind of development: new-school,
perhaps?  But it represents the author&#x27;s willingness to back off and leave part
of the story truly in the hands of the player, spelling out the implications of
success and failure while leaving the choices to the protagonist.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I approve, of course.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever your reaction to the later aspects of the game, you&#x27;re likely to find
it at the very least an entertaining play.  At its best moments it is also
surprising and thought-provoking.  There is an idea at the very core of it that
I would like to talk about, as it touches upon IF and as it interacts with the
time-travel scene, but I haven&#x27;t done thinking about it yet.  And, in any case,
that belongs in a spoiler-proofed venue.  In the meantime, go and play the
game.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Archaeology</title>
        <author><name>Paul O&#x27;Brian</name></author>
        <published>2001-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010629/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010629/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Zork I was the first text adventure game I ever played, and I played it a lot.
That game occupied many, many hours of my time and, to this day, it remains one
of only a few Infocom games I was ever able to solve without hints, due solely
to my stubborn and relentless attention to it.  Between those marathon
childhood sessions and the occasions on which I&#x27;ve replayed it since, I have
walked those underground caverns many times, and their geography is so fixed in
my mind that I think if I should ever find myself transported there, I could
navigate with ease.  Or, at least, that&#x27;s how I &lt;em&gt;used&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to feel, before I
started playing Dungeon and got my internal map thoroughly whacked.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dungeon is the predecessor to the Zork games; it was MIT&#x27;s answer to Crowther
and Woods&#x27; &amp;quot;Adventure&amp;quot; and, much like that game, it lived on a mainframe, since
its prodigious size was too great for the personal computers of its day. When
the authors decided to make a commercial go of the text adventure business,
they chopped Dungeon into three sections, rearranging the geography and adding
some new elements to each chapter, especially the second and third. I&#x27;ve played
the Zork games many times, but I had always wanted to play the mainframe
version in order to better understand just what was added and what subtracted.
So when I opened the WinGlk version of Andrew Plotkin&#x27;s C translation of the
game, I was prepared for some shifts in layout compared to my deeply-graven
memories of Zork I.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I wasn&#x27;t prepared for, though, was the way in which Dungeon gleefully
confounds any sense of actual geography in exchange for making the game map
another obstacle to be overcome. In Dungeon, connections that line up properly
(for example, leaving one room to the south and entering the adjoining room
from the north) are the exception rather than the rule. Instead, you may go
west and find that to get back to where you came from, you have to go west
&lt;em&gt;again&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. In a recent article about &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.brasslantern.org&#x2F;writers&#x2F;iftheory&#x2F;setting.html&quot;&gt;crafting a good setting for fantasy IF&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
Emily Short addressed this tendency:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
[In] the ideal IF setting, the parts of the setting relate to each other in
comprehensible ways. Things are located sensibly. I dislike mazes not only
because you do have to map them but also because they interfere with and
scramble up the intuitive sense of place that I otherwise build up as I play. 
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this sense, almost the entirety of Dungeon functions as a maze, and any
coherent sense of place that might emerge is bound to get smacked down as soon
as the next exit is explored. I have a pretty good knack for mapping in my
head, and thus don&#x27;t tend to make a map while playing IF but, with this game,
there was no way I could pursue that strategy.  Thus, grumbling, I hauled out
my copy of GUEmap and tried diligently to record the tortured web of
interconnections that make up the Dungeon landscape. When I finally finished, I
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ifarchive.org&#x2F;if-archive&#x2F;solutions&#x2F;maps&#x2F;Dungeon.zip&quot;&gt;uploaded the results to
GMD&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; so that
other players like myself won&#x27;t have to struggle through the game&#x27;s mazes on
their own.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And oh, the mazes — in addition to the general illogic of its structure,
Dungeon also sports several mazes, all of which carry the &amp;quot;warped connections&amp;quot;
tendency to its furthest extreme. Of course, when seen from the historical
perspective, these mazes make sense: Adventure had mazes, and since mazes are
one of the easiest kinds of puzzles to create, it follows that the game
attempting to top Adventure would have mazes of its own. What Dungeon does,
though, is to twist the knife: not only does it present the player with mazes,
it confounds the typical &amp;quot;drop item and map&amp;quot; strategy by having an NPC come
along and remove or rearrange those items, taunting the player with comments
like &amp;quot;My, I wonder who left this fine hot pepper sandwich here?&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When viewed with a modern eye, obstacles like this make clear how different is
the stance of modern IF from its ancestors. Dungeon set itself up unambiguously
as the player&#x27;s antagonist, and it wasn&#x27;t particularly concerned with telling a
story, nor even with describing a world. Plot is nonexistent, and fabulous
treasures are described with perfunctory lines like &amp;quot;You see nothing special
about the sapphire bracelet.&amp;quot; Instead, Dungeon puts its energies into confusing
and confounding the player, and wacky map connections are but the tip of the
iceberg. Along with the aforementioned mazes, there&#x27;s the light source, which
always runs out at the worst possible times. There&#x27;s the Round Room, guaranteed
to tangle any map. There are the &amp;quot;secret word&amp;quot; puzzles, some of which still
perplex me to this day, even though I know how they operate. And of course,
there&#x27;s the thief, whose annoyances are both numerous and legendary. Dungeon
wants nothing more than to see you fail, and it&#x27;s not overly concerned with how
much fun you might be having. As Robb Sherwin asserted on rec.games.int-fiction
recently, &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;groups.google.com&#x2F;groups?ic=1&amp;amp;selm=3b1d33a9.613499395%40voder&quot;&gt;Zork hates its player&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today&#x27;s IF, by contrast, works a bit harder to collaborate with the player,
with the aim of creating a shared experience, both in setting and plot. Even
the Zork games moved in this direction, at least in comparison to Dungeon,
mitigating some of the latter game&#x27;s greatest excesses by straightening out
many map connections, allowing more flexibility with the permanent light
source, and providing a bit more description from time to time. The ways in
which Infocom itself engineered the shift from &amp;quot;text-based puzzle games&amp;quot; to
actual interactive fiction is a subject for another article, but what&#x27;s become
clear is that where the emphasis was once on opposition, it has shifted
steadily to cooperation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my mind, this shift is both appropriate and necessary, and what playing
Dungeon illuminated for me is that this movement towards collaborative IF is
not the same thing as the concurrent movement towards &amp;quot;literary IF&amp;quot;, though
they are often confused for one another. I can envision a game that, like
Dungeon, has no particular literary pretensions, but unlike Dungeon, isn&#x27;t
trying to undermine its player through the use of arbitrary techniques like
twisty map connections and unreliable light sources. I would assert that
collaborative IF doesn&#x27;t need to tell a story, and it certainly doesn&#x27;t need to
aspire to literary greatness, but it does need to work with the player to
create a rich, interactive world, and it does need to be concerned with giving
the player a positive, fun experience. Of course collaborative IF can be
puzzleless, but it needn&#x27;t be — puzzles can be part of the fun, as long
as they aren&#x27;t geared towards forcing restarts after 800 moves, or making the
player do tedious, menial work. The move away from antagonistic IF is the
reason why things like mazes, limited light sources, and starvation puzzles are
met with a chorus of jeers these days, but the elimination of these elements
doesn&#x27;t necessarily dictate anything in particular about how literary or
puzzleless a game might be.  Instead, the change makes the whole experience of
IF more about fun than bloody-minded perseverance; playing Dungeon makes it
clear how necessary this change was, and how far we&#x27;ve come since those
mainframe days.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>A Step</title>
        <author><name>Emily Short</name></author>
        <published>2001-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010622/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010622/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So Far&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is one of those games that everyone is supposed to play. It&#x27;s the
source of numerous jokes and references in other games; it is the longest (and
some would say the most serious and most angst-ridden) of Zarf&#x27;s games, which
earns it attention in and of itself. And, written in 1996, it is old enough to
stand in the position of a classic in this brief community. (If the reviewer&#x27;s
job is to tell people whether to play the game, I&#x27;m done now: you should,
absolutely. But you knew that.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of its considerable reputation, I tried repeatedly to play it myself,
and failed the first four or five times. The opening of the game is
involving — almost oppressively so. I felt almost claustrophobic playing it,
so vividly are the crowd and the summer heat evoked, so that it was a relief to
escape from the first of the game&#x27;s environments. At the same time, I had the
sense that I had left behind some important bit of plot, something that I could
or should be interacting with, and I wasn&#x27;t sure whether I would ever be
allowed to go back. The subsequent puzzles stumped me, in part because I was
trying to make logical sense of the history of the worlds in which I was
traveling, in part because I am not particularly good at visualizing complex
machinery in the way required to manipulate it properly. One of the times I
gave up, I complained to a friend that this was a game that required to be read
slowly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am no opponent of dense prose, and I don&#x27;t mind spending time reading. But I
have always found that when I am deeply involved in a piece of interactive
fiction, a sense of urgency builds so that I am too impatient to read deeply
and receptively. I want short pieces of prose, not long paragraphs. And I
don&#x27;t want flowery writing, either, or anything that stands between me and the
most rapid possible comprehension. How am I supposed to know what to do when I
am busy trying to ferret out the significance of lines upon lines of metaphor?
Correspondingly I try for brevity in my own IF writing; I try to layer
description through deep implementation, so that one description leads to
another rather than the first surface description hitting the player with pages
of prose. So I struggled with &lt;em&gt;So Far&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, because my normal mode of playing IF is
one in which I bash at things in order to understand them. I explore and
summarize first, then tinker with the details to see what they will yield up.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#x27;s the wrong way to play this game, if one can talk about right and
wrong approaches. This is the kind of game where you not only have to read
each piece carefully and thoughtfully the first time, you also have to stand
permanently apart from what&#x27;s going on. You&#x27;re doing things that make no real
logical sense — by the hundred, it seems. Graham Nelson&#x27;s Player&#x27;s Bill of
Rights is triumphantly defied by some of the acts of intuitive leaping,
save-and-restore decipherment, and hindsight required to get through the game
properly. Even so I only managed with liberal use of Lucian Smith&#x27;s
Invisiclues and suggestions from friends on ifMUD. As Duncan Stevens says in
his recent SPAG review of the same game, &lt;em&gt;So Far&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; works thematically, but the
plot doesn&#x27;t entirely make sense.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&#x27;s involving, as I said, because of the vivid landscapes and the
portentous sense of meaning that pervades everything, but it is perhaps not
immersive in the classic sense. The save-and-restore method of solving
problems is one that quickly teaches you to disregard your PC&#x27;s life; danger is
diminished thereby. (Adam Cadre&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;Varicella&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; carries this effect perhaps to
its ultimate extreme, but it is present here as well.) I didn&#x27;t feel that I
was the player character, exactly. After all, he would have had access to the
background knowledge to explain (and wouldn&#x27;t that be convenient?) exactly what
was going on between himself and his beloved(?) Aessa, among other things. I
the player could only guess. The experience in that respect was a bit like
reading a work of static fiction in which much of the background is
deliberately withheld. I&#x27;m reminded of trying to read &lt;em&gt;The English Patient.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
(I didn&#x27;t like it as much as the movie and stopped after page 2.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus far we have fiendish puzzles, a density of prose and concept that
challenges the average approach to IF, and a certain amount of narrative
distance between player and PC. Something relatively inaccessible, in short.
But what the game gains by being obscure, by demanding intellectual attention
at a high order, is the ability to address itself to abstracts. Interactive
fiction is a medium that principally deals with the concrete: objects that you
can pick up and move around in standardized ways, without resorting to too
complex or elusive a vocabulary. Various people have proposed, for instance,
NPC interaction systems that would make use of complicated verbs such as
PROVOKE, APOLOGIZE, etc., but I have yet to see such a system that worked
particularly well, despite having tried to devise one myself. Likewise
important choices of a personal nature — not choices about how to fend off the
alligator who is about to bite off your leg if you don&#x27;t feed him the ham, but
choices about ethics or emotion — have always to be cast in terms of physical
actions. Jigsaw, Spider and Web, and Tapestry all come to mind as having
moments where the player&#x27;s moral choice is encapsulated in a physical action,
the significance of which has been carefully developed and spelled out in
advance. What &lt;em&gt;So Far&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; achieves that distinguishes itself even from these (which
are themselves moments of high artistry in the genre) is not teaching the
player how to regard a single action as representative of moral choice, but
presenting the whole world in such a way that it seems redolent of such
choices, tying the physical environment intimately to the emotional one in ways
that are sometimes visible only in retrospect.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To say that it relies on symbolic vocabulary is to understate the issue.
Jigsaw, for instance, relies on symbolic vocabulary as well, especially in the
endgame. But Nelson&#x27;s symbols are isolated and recognizable, and stand out
from the landscape in their symbolic significance like a girl in a red dress.
&#x27;Note this!&#x27; they say. And they are organized with a tidy symmetry, perfect
and mathematical, so that the meaning of anything unexplained may be worked out
by its relations to other symbols and the oppositions between them. Plotkin&#x27;s
symbolism is merged wholly with the landscape; it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the landscape. The
pieces are polyvalent and connotative, any given thing suggesting an array of
connections and meanings, not denoting a single concept in its purity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure whether any subsequent work has approached it in this 
regard. I am not sure that anyone has tried.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>A Brief Flash</title>
        <author><name>Jonathan Rosebaugh</name></author>
        <published>2001-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010615/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010615/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
                 HOPE is the thing with feathers&lt;br&gt;
                    That perches in the soul,&lt;br&gt;
              And sings the tune without the words,&lt;br&gt;
                     And never stops at all&lt;br&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; Emily Dickinson&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, I hate TADS games. I&#x27;m not sure exactly why, but even in the best
games, I find myself wishing that I was playing an Inform game. It is extremely
rare that I find a TADS game capable of making me forget this. In fact, there
have only been two. Glowgrass is one of those games.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like every game, Glowgrass has its flaws. Like a very few games, the story in
Glowgrass covers over these flaws. The story packs a huge punch for such a
small game, covering as it does themes of hope for humanity and for the
individual.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many science-fiction books where humanity is out among the stars, Earth has
been forgotten. Whether due to rendering the planet inhabitable or just plain
leaving it behind, humanity quickly loses sight of its roots. &lt;em&gt;Foundation&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
visited this by describing archeologists&#x27; searches for the original planet of
mankind, but even then, they could not pin it down. In Glowgrass, they have
found that, but have lost track of what humanity &lt;em&gt;was&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You play an archeologist, crash-landing at the site of an Ancient dwelling. You
lose almost all of your tools, requiring you to lean on your wits alone to find
some way to get back to civilization.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: From here on, there may be spoilers for various parts of the game. If
you do not want to read these spoilers, go play the game. It&#x27;s worth it. Thank
you.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humanity has fallen. Normally this would entail a story somewhat like &lt;em&gt;The
Postman&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, with a strong young man leading humanity out of a neo-dark age.
Unfortunatly, there does not seem to have been a strong young man available at
the time, as humanity quickly went extinct. All that&#x27;s left are houses and cars
and such — and one young girl who turned herself into an AI.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marie is your guide to Post-Apocalyptic Earth, which looks a whole lot like
Pre-Apocalyptic Earth except that you and she are the only people alive on the
planet. You initially find her skeleton, with the mind-downloading device still
sitting on her head. When you bring her up for the first time, she is scared
— her whole world has fallen to pieces. She goes through the stages of
grieving very quickly, perhaps too quickly. She decides to trust you, and the
two of you set about finding a way to get back to civilization.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game worked for me, not because of the flashing prose, but because of the
themes. I&#x27;ve always been partial to a good AI story — in fact, I have a
WIP with one on the backburner right now. And I like a good end-of-the-world
story, when it&#x27;s done well. And, of course, I like a good alien story, both
with metaphorical and literal aliens. Let&#x27;s take those in order, shall we.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI has showed up in a few IF games, usually good ones. There may be a
correlation here; I hope so. There&#x27;s something alluring about the prospect of
creating something in our image. Zarf said it; We are made in the image of God,
and what is God but the Creator? An AI would, by definition, be a very alien
thing, but to my mind, the most successful AIs have been the ones that were
like us.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marie is very much like us. She has been dragged into the future head-long and
forced to adjust to radically different situations, and in typical
monkey-fashion, she copes. What&#x27;s more, she manages to take charge of the
situation, and get the PC back to civilization.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mankind is dead; long live mankind. We&#x27;re tenacious. Even when we do wipe
ourselves back to barbarism, we tend to stick around. In Glowgrass, all that&#x27;s
left is Marie and whatever the PC&#x27;s people have become, but even still, we
remain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most alien thing in this game is the PC. At the end, we are given a glimpse
of how much has changed over the years. Humanity has altered even the very
basic compounds on which our bodies operate, yet we remain able to relate to
humans from before the plague. The most distressingly alien thing about them is
that they seem to have forgotten Earth and what we were like, though this is
understandable, given the time spans that must be involved.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in the end, it&#x27;s the story that takes the prize. We have characterization,
we have plot, we have, here and there, a few puzzles, we have tension, and we
have a resolution. We also have what I interpret to be a promise of a sequel,
for which I am waiting eagerly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Don&#x27;t Put Me On Hold</title>
        <author><name>Adam Biltcliffe</name></author>
        <published>2001-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010525/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010525/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: In the review which follows, I&#x27;ve tried to avoid spoiling
anything which you can&#x27;t find out for yourself within the first two or three
moves. However, it is my belief that &lt;em&gt;FailSafe&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is best experienced with no
prior knowledge at all. My recommendation is this: it&#x27;s an excellent game,
so go and play it now, without reading the rest of this review. Of course,
some people might argue that that defeats the point of a review, to which
I&#x27;m inclined to agree. So, trust me and play it now, or read the review
first, it&#x27;s your choice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gametext rounded&quot;&gt;
        Bzzt. Crackle. *Static*
&lt;br&#x2F;&gt;
&quot;...hello? Hello? Can... me? .. Anyone! Hel.... Need.. hello?&quot;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, a voice is pleading for help. This is the first hint we have of
&lt;em&gt;FailSafe&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&#x27;s subject matter: the title screen, and even the author&#x27;s original
announcement of the game, remain carefully silent regarding anything more
than the author and betatesters. Then abruptly we are dropped into a broken,
poorly-transmitted radio conversation with an unknown NPC and left to fend
for ourselves.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This conversation, as it turns out, comprises the entire game. During the
brief introduction, we discover that the voice on the other end is the sole
survivor of some terrible disaster, and is now trapped on board a crippled
spaceship falling towards the moon. The interaction in these first few
exchanges feels very natural (except for one minor programming issue), such
that it&#x27;s actually slightly disconcerting to realise that the conversation
has turned into the game without you noticing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, you can order the unseen survivor around the wreck of the
spacecraft very much like playing a conventional IF game. The style of the
descriptions in the first person is reminiscent of &lt;em&gt;LASH&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, and, to an extent,
older, more conventional first-person games, but &lt;em&gt;FailSafe&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is much more
adventurous as regards conversation between the player and the protagonist.
At points, the unseen NPC will ask questions, such as &amp;quot;shall I read the
display to you?&amp;quot; — personally, I felt that this did a lot to make the
dialogue seem more realistic and less like a conventional IF game (and,
thankfully, such questions can be ignored entirely if you so desire). There
are points, however, where the voice will come back with the same, sometimes
quite lengthy, chunk of text in response to repeated actions, or even
attempt obviously dangerous actions again in response to your command, with
the same response. However, I found myself succumbing to an effect I&#x27;ve
noticed before (something I seem to recall Emily Short saying she hoped
players would do when playing &lt;em&gt;Galatea&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;): namely, once it became obvious that
repeating actions gave rise to mimesis-breaking responses, I started
avoiding doing it, because by this point, I was getting absorbed in the
game. Maybe this was partly due to the air of mystery that accompanied the
announcement but, as the protagonist explores the wreckage of the ship,
there are subtle clues that something is not quite right.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to talking the survivor through trying to save what&#x27;s left of
the ship and&#x2F;or escaping from it, there&#x27;s a secondary dialogue of a sort
going on with some kind of computer program in response to the incoming
information. As well as giving background information, this helps us see the
PC&#x27;s role a little more clearly, and the incoming battle reports give a
sense of the wider background.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;FailSafe&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is not a difficult game — there aren&#x27;t really any puzzles to speak
of in the traditional sense, meaning that it&#x27;s not hard to reach the end of
the game with a little patience. However, there&#x27;s the ongoing puzzle-like
element of trying to piece together a coherent vision of the environment
from the fractured descriptions given by the NPC. It&#x27;s not so easy to work
out exactly what is where within the rooms of the ship, although this
problem seems more forgivable in light of &lt;em&gt;FailSafe&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&#x27;s context than it does in
other, more traditional games. One thing it&#x27;s a shame to see missing is that
the protagonist never varies his or her phrasing when redescribing rooms,
which would be useful to the player as well as strengthening mimesis.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One complaint a lot of people had about this game was the fact that,
presumably in an attempt to increase immersion, almost all the standard meta
verbs are disabled; in particular, it&#x27;s impossible to save and restore. The
relative shortness goes some way towards alleviating this, but there are
multiple possible outcomes, and investigating all of them would be tedious
on an interpreter which doesn&#x27;t allow you to save your commands and feed
them back in. Additionally, some commands, notably movement, can&#x27;t be
shortened as much as usual, but there&#x27;s not a great amount of moving around
involved here in any case, so it seemed to me as though this particular
change served mainly to reinforce the fact that the player is giving orders
to another than mentally ordering herself around, by forcing the command to
be phrased as such (&lt;code&gt;GO UP&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;). However, I can well imagine others disagreeing
on this score.  Happily, &lt;code&gt;X&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;L&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Z&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; still work with their usual
meanings.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it was because of the illusion of talking to a person rather than a
parser, but I found myself spelling out commands in longhand much more
frequently anyway: &lt;code&gt;LOOK AT THE CONSOLE&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; rather than &lt;code&gt;X CONSOLE&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and similar
(although I&#x27;ve noticed myself doing that anyway in the past, often when I
suddenly get the feeling that an invisible presence is watching me type.
Maybe I&#x27;m paranoid, but I digress).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;FailSafe&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is not a conventional work of IF, although I&#x27;d hesitate to label it
as &#x27;experimental&#x27;. It&#x27;s not an experiment — the departures it makes from
the &#x27;standard&#x27; model of IF are all carefully chosen for their effect in
presenting the story, such that it is the story and the world behind it,
rather than any kind of &#x27;gimmick&#x27;, which dominate at least my memories of
the game. I&#x27;m hoping it&#x27;s also an example for authors of how the effort
involved in doing something differently to the way most IF authoring systems
expect is really worth doing if that&#x27;s how you think the story is best told.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Puzzles vs. History</title>
        <author><name>Adam Cadre</name></author>
        <published>2001-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010518/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010518/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lost New York&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; by Neil deMause sends the player character bouncing around in
time, from 1880 to 1905 to 1954 to 1780 to 2040.  But none of these dates has
anywhere near as much effect on the shape of the game as its year of
publication: 1996.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For in 1996, the conventional wisdom asserted that the remaining audience for
text adventures was after just that: text adventures. Games were essentially
just series of puzzles, with the story as a backdrop, the model world as set
decoration.  Yes, that backdrop and set decoration could be and often was
masterfully designed, but the idea that simply building a model world for the
player to poke around in or telling a story in which the player could
participate constituted valid IF only gained widespread acceptance over the
subsequent five years, as increasingly daring games placed less and less
emphasis on puzzles and were rewarded with plaudits from an audience that found
it rather liked that sort of thing.  But in 1996, how the audience might
respond was an open question.  Given the amount of effort that goes into a
full-length work of IF, most authors elected to go with the proven approach.
&lt;em&gt;Lost New York&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is no exception.  But while it follows the crowd, it does so with
obvious reluctance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of time travel, let&#x27;s jump back about 400 years, to the time of
Shakespeare.  But not our Shakespeare -- this Shakespeare lives in an England
where theater audiences are mad about juggling acts.  Day after day, the Globe
is witness to trio after trio of balls, pins and torches being flung into the
air.  But the audiences didn&#x27;t want to see &lt;em&gt;just&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; juggling; they wanted the
juggling folded into a little story. Enter Shakespeare, who soars to fame on
the strength of &amp;quot;Romeo and Juliet&amp;quot;, in which a pair of young people fall in
love at a masked ball(the chief entertainment there: juggling), but then the
boy&#x27;s friend and the girl&#x27;s cousin get into a ill-fated juggling contest and it
all goes downhill from there.  Now Shakespeare decides he might like to try
writing a history, perhaps something involving King Henry V... yes, a piece
tracing his evolution from carousing prince to the inspirational leader of his
countrymen in a great victory over the French.  But he can&#x27;t just tell that
story -- where&#x27;s the juggling?  If there&#x27;s no juggling, it&#x27;s not a real play!
So the first act ends up foregrounding a bunch of jugglers at the bar while
Falstaff and Prince Hal talk in the background, and proceeds to the point where
the jugglers accompanying the army are told that the English have won the
battle... and the audience response is tepid because while the historical stuff
is interesting, the juggling isn&#x27;t as accomplished as that in in &lt;em&gt;Rito and
Imita&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.  Shakespeare is left to mutter to himself about the constraints of the
medium.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, it&#x27;s clear that in &lt;em&gt;Lost New York&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; deMause&#x27;s heart is in the
geographical and historical material.  Virtually all the prose is extremely
deft, but never is the writing more alive, more joyous, than when you die and
the author gets to tell you another wacky story about a long-dead mayor; never
are the quips funnier than when they&#x27;re playing off the geography of the city
(try going east from the City Hall area in 1880, or north into Hell&#x27;s Kitchen
later on.)  The fact that the game begins with a slideshow and ends with a
bibliography is another indication of where the author&#x27;s interests lie.  Hint:
it&#x27;s not in fiddling around with hairpins and stopwatches.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But because this was written in 1996, the author felt obliged to fill it with
juggl-- I mean, puzzles.  And these are mostly not very good, being chiefly of
the type where you&#x27;re wandering around and find a fishing pole, which you take
because, well, it&#x27;s implemented; later on you find a stream, and go fishing
because, well, that must be what the pole&#x27;s for; you catch a fish and, when you
cut it open to cook it, a key falls out.  What was the key doing in the fish?
Well, one of the conventions of the genre at the time was that you weren&#x27;t
supposed to ask questions like that.  That&#x27;s not actually a puzzle from &lt;em&gt;Lost
New York&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, but many similar ones abound.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, while the &amp;quot;take everything that&#x27;s not nailed down, look under and
behind and inside everything that is&amp;quot; ethic works fine in a dungeon, it gets to
be a little absurd when transplanted to the island of Manhattan.  In &lt;em&gt;Lost New York&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;,
Manhattan has like twelve things.  And that&#x27;s too many.  (Bet you thought
I was going to go a different way with that, huh?)  Again, to avoid spoilers,
I&#x27;ll disguise the details a bit.  Let&#x27;s say that the Upper West Side, circa
1965, has been reduced to a single location with a mailbox in it.  Now, the
problem is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; that each street corner should be a separate location, nor
that every item in every store and every apartment should be implemented. As it
stands, the location works just fine as a representative area of the Upper West
Side, and the mailbox works just fine as a representative mailbox.  BUT!  As
soon as you fish around in the mailbox and pull out a live monkey (which you
then stuff into your knapsack) you are no longer dealing with the Platonic
Mailbox -- you&#x27;re dealing with a specific, highly unusual mailbox.  And by
extension, this is no longer just a representative street corner: it&#x27;s the
particular street corner with the strange monkey-containing mailbox.  And once
players lose the sense that the locations they&#x27;re visiting are representative,
they&#x27;re no longer wandering around Manhattan; they&#x27;re navigating a diorama of
Manhattan with twelve things in it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it didn&#x27;t have to be this way.  &lt;em&gt;Lost New York&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is as much about the New
Yorks that might have been as the ones that actually have, and in that spirit, I
can&#x27;t help but muse about what might have happened had Neil deMause had his
notes stolen one day in 1995.  Disheartened, he puts off the project for a few
years, till his enthusiasm revives -- only now the IF landscape is different.
&lt;em&gt;A Mind Forever Voyaging&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is no longer a low-selling oddball; &lt;em&gt;lots&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of games now
revolve around exploration instead of dinking around with inventory.  And so
this alternate, post-&#x27;96 version of &lt;em&gt;Lost New York&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; takes on a different shape.
Instead of players getting little more than a glimpse of New York&#x27;s evolution,
whatever gets mentioned in passing as they&#x27;re messing around with goats and
baseballs in curiously limited regions of the city, they can now roam the
entirety of the city freely, watching the different neighborhoods evolve.
Perhaps the interaction with figures who clearly fascinate the author -- Robert
Moses, Emma Goldman, the various mayors -- is more substantial... leading to
more New Yorks that might have been, perhaps?  A fully implemented Moses-free
New York, say, or one where Goldman&#x27;s ideals took root... perhaps even a
modern-day New Amsterdam, if you diverge early enough.  And hey, TADS has
multimedia now: why not throw some pictures into the mix?... oh, and...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...and at this point I&#x27;ve got the blueprints for a 21st-century skyscraper and
am waving them at the base of the Empire State Building. The game has been
written, and if deMause is anything like me, the idea of revisiting a
project that was long ago declared done is hardly an appealing one...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...but hey, it&#x27;s New York.  If it were ever really finished, we wouldn&#x27;t have
that old story about the visitor from Nebraska.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>A Game Untangled</title>
        <author><name>Emily Short</name></author>
        <published>2001-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010511/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010511/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is one of those games of which it feels almost pointless to write a review
because so many people have already reviewed it; besides, it&#x27;s widely enough
played to be one of the canonical games that newsgroup posters use to
illustrate a wide variety of things. If you&#x27;ve already played it, you already
know your opinion.  If you haven&#x27;t, you probably still have an idea of whether
you&#x27;d like it or not, unless you&#x27;ve been living under a box for the last
several years (or not paying attention to the IF community, which is, for the
purposes of this review, the same thing).  What remains to be said that has not
already been said by reviews, by r*if, by the numerous XYZZYs it received? Why
do I bother?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People have talked about this game because of how it handles conveying
information to the player, providing only gradually the things that the player
character must already be well aware of; about how it restricts and controls
interaction with the non-player characters, managing characterization in other
ways; about how it filters in the necessary hints gradually, coaching you when
you get things wrong.  The central conceit of the game -- that you are
recounting an experience to an interrogator, and that all your actions already
lie in the past -- makes all of these things possible and seamless.  And there
is also the technical cleverness of the gadgets: the protagonist is given a
large selection of entertaining toys to play with, which, like good IF toys,
need to be figured out and then reapplied in a variety of different ways.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are also aspects of this game&#x27;s success that have nothing to do with
the elegance of the design as a design, however.  Indeed, I think they tend to
go underexplored for the simple reason that the design is so very good.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of it is the setting.  The interrogation chamber, the technological
gadgets, the cold-war-esque tension between two superpowers of escalating
genius and desperation: these are elements of the science fiction that colored
my childhood.  In the 80s I was perennially conscious of the possibility that
we would find ourselves at war at any time: a war which might take the form of
nuclear disaster but might also somehow involve me personally in a situation of
hideous choice.  In retrospect this was half because I was young enough to
think the world revolved around me, and half because of my reading matter.
Sylvia Louise Engdahl&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;The Far Side of Evil&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, which featured a prolonged
sequence of inprisonment and interrogation, made a particularly strong
impression on me.  (It also fed into my existing sense of persecution by my
schoolmates, who had a habit of snatching the book from my hands when I tried
to read at recess and turning it upside down.  When I proceeded to read the
book upside down the trick lost interest for them, apparently.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spider and Web touches on the same trope: the great struggle for the fate of the
world becomes embodied in a struggle of wills between two extraordinary people,
the captured spy and the interrogating enemy. Whether it would have the same
effect for someone born ten years after me, I don&#x27;t know; the world has
changed, obviously.  That stark alignment of the universe certainly no longer
seems to apply to real life, and I am much more frightened of what might happen
in some small, unregarded country; danger now seems to come from the unexpected
fanatic, not the ancient and inevitable enemy who is our equal in strength.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening text of the game sets the stage for this very nicely, putting the
protagonist in a country that feels like eastern Europe viewed through American
eyes:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gametext rounded&quot;&gt;
        On the whole, it was worth the trip. The plains really were broad and
grain-gold, if scarred with fences and agricultural crawlers. The mountains
were overwhelming. And however much of the capital city is crusted with squat
brick and faceless concrete hulks, there are still flashes of its historic
charm. You&#x27;ve seen spires above the streets -- tiny green parks below
tenements -- hidden jewels of fountains beyond walls. Any bland alley can
concealbalconies wrought into iron gardens, fiery mosaics, a tree or bed of
flowers nurtured by who knows who.
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the sense of the grandeur of the countryside and the startling beauty of
a place that has been around for hundreds of years.  My parents live in a
suburb that didn&#x27;t really exist fifty years ago, where the local Historical
Monument is a log house some guy built in the late 19th century.  There&#x27;s also
a pretty famous house from the 1920s.  Going from that to, e.g., Prague leaves
one with the impression that the universe has just expanded in a totally
unexpected direction.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also embedded in the description, though, is a foreshadowing of the theme of
concealment that pervades everything to come: this is a landscape of secrets,
even outside the interrogation chamber.  Partly this is because in a
totalitarian regime (and we are invited to see the enemy as such), any scrap of
individuality must be privately guarded -- but the game reminds us again and
again that the individuality exists, even (or perhaps especially) in the PC&#x27;s
captor.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the narrative proceeds -- and I won&#x27;t describe it here -- the topics of
cold-war discourse play themselves out: how much power belongs in anyone&#x27;s
hands?  Are We really very different from Them? What of our common humanity do
we sacrifice if we identify ourselves too eagerly with one side or the other?
None of these are precisely new questions, but they work here, I think, because
they are consistently brought to your attention through the personal
relationship of captor and captured.  And the choices that you have to make
become charged with ideological significance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the linearity of the game, its ultimate meaning is entirely in your
hands.  Or perhaps entirely in your mind.  There are a couple of endgame
options -- &lt;em&gt;important&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; options, things that sum up the whole meaning of the
story -- but you&#x27;re not told how they play out, one way or the other.  You get
to choose, but you don&#x27;t get to know all the final ramifications.  People have
found this unsatisfying, and griped.  I myself found it unsatisfying, and
griped.  There&#x27;s something about it that is nonetheless true to morality in
real life: not only do we often have to make our decisions blindly, but we
cannot always know for certain even after the fact what the outcomes were or
would have been.  The difficult ending shifts the onus of decision entirely on
you: you pick one way or another because that&#x27;s what seems right to you.  The
author will not afford you the kindness of telling you what you should have
done.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>On Common Ground</title>
        <author><name>Emily Short</name></author>
        <published>2001-04-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-04-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010413/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010413/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Warning: the following is by necessity somewhat spoilery; though I 
have tried to avoid explicit information about the events of the 
game, reading it may affect your enjoyment if you haven&#x27;t played it 
yet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stephen Granade&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;Common Ground&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is a short, friendly game, more 
character-piece and story than puzzle.  By giving you the perspective 
of each of three protagonists in turn, it sketches in the 
relationships between members of a small family, showing you both 
sides of each point of conflict.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technique of multiple viewpoints is a nifty one, used here with 
nuance and attention to detail.  Object descriptions change, and new 
ones pop in and out of view, depending on what the character might be 
expected to notice or understand.  The effect is subtler than the use 
of the same technique in &lt;em&gt;Exhibition&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and less broadly humorous than 
&lt;em&gt;Being Andrew Plotkin&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;: the characters are distinguished from each 
other by smaller variations, a separation of a few degrees only. 
Particularly fine is the way different people hear the &lt;em&gt;same&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; bits of 
conversation differently.  Wording, tone, and sometimes even factual 
content changes, depending on what is going on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise subtle is the handling of what you have to do in the game. 
Most of the activity is straightforward.  There is little that would 
count as a puzzle; there are a number of required actions (especially 
if you are one particular character), some of which are a bit boring, 
but this is exactly to the point.  They convey perfectly the 
irritation of the situation: leading a rather ordinary life full of 
small frustrations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, however, all this is in service of presenting a static 
situation, and the nuance of game detail is not quite matched by 
nuance of character depth.  By the end, you perceive how the 
characters misunderstand and undervalue each other, but they are 
still, in essence, rather stock characters: the rebellious teenage 
girl, the overworked mother, the slightly boozy stepfather.  One can 
sympathize with them to a degree, but they don&#x27;t distinguish 
themselves with much particularity.  They lack pasts.  They lack 
hobbies, and external interests.  This sort of thing makes it 
difficult to care deeply about them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also problematic, and on similar terms, is the restriction of what 
one is allowed to say.  Interaction between characters uses the 
device of TALK TO, which has been used more and more in recent games, 
and to good effect in things like &lt;em&gt;Kaged&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, I think.  But this is a 
game that rests upon its interaction between people, in which the 
relationships are the whole point; and it is a bit disappointing not 
to be able to try certain conversational approaches.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implementation of the physical environment is likewise a bit 
under-immersive.  The house doesn&#x27;t feel like a real house to me; it 
feels like a stage set up with a few key props for the drama.  What 
is there is precisely what must be there, and nothing more.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To all of these criticisms there are two perfectly reasonable 
objections.  One is that the nature of implementing this game -- one 
in which three different characters experience the same events -- 
severely restricts what one can do, since a PC cannot be forced to 
recapitulate the behavior of the NPC in an earlier scene.  The more 
immersive and fully interactive the game becomes, the more difficult 
it is to police player actions in a way that will keep the outcome 
consistent.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second, less technical and more aesthetic, is that the characters 
are constrained by their nature.  They are bored, dissatisfied, and 
just managing to scrape through in life.  Their lack of deep 
dimension says something about how they perceive themselves. 
Likewise, being who they are, they will only say certain things.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect of all this is a bit like acting out a play -- a somewhat 
minimalist play, at that, one of those modern ones with no 
conceivable happy ending.  It presents the misery and disaffection of 
suburban life, and constrains the player character(s) in such a way 
that none of them really has a chance to rise above it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what of the ending?  There is an important decision to be made, 
and this is the one point at which you are not, in fact, constrained 
to one course of action.  You can choose which of two things to do -- 
but then you are never shown the outcome of the choice.  It is easy 
enough to imagine what might ensue from either one, but in the 
absence of any result at all, it&#x27;s hard to feel the significance of 
the decision.  If you feel the power of the choice, it is entirely 
because you imagine it yourself -- sketching in implications and 
likely outcomes from your own personal experience, drawing on nothing 
in the game for support.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m not sure that it would have been wise to spell out, either in a 
detailed interactive piece or in a cut-scene, what happens the next 
day or the next week in lurid detail.  Such an addition might have 
overbalanced the game, taking attention from the delicacy of the 
chapters that are already there.  But it still does seem as though it 
would have been possible -- and would have much strengthened the game 
-- to make the decision itself more intense; to set up its emotional 
importance to the characters more; to give it, one way or the other, 
the force that it ought to have.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we have, then, is a well-crafted and subtly considered piece 
that succeeds in many of its small goals, but possibly fails at the 
larger one of involving the player deeply.  The story it tells seems 
abridged and insufficient, and the characters never entirely free 
themselves from stereotype.  At the same time, it takes on a 
challenge rarely met in interactive fiction: it is entirely a story 
about nebulous human decisions and personal relationships, without 
wacky devices, melodramatic scenes, physical danger and pending 
disaster.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>A Dream of Lethe</title>
        <author><name>Gunther Schmidl</name></author>
        <published>2001-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010323/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010323/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here be, as always, spoilers. You have been warned.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dan Shiovitz&#x27; &lt;em&gt;Lethe Flow Phoenix&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is different from other games.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, its style of narration at the start of the game reminded me of C. 
S. Lewis&#x27; &lt;em&gt;The Magician&#x27;s Nephew&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; or, perhaps more flattering, Tolkien&#x27;s 
&lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; with editorial comments like&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gametext rounded&quot;&gt;
        The rock is oval, fairly heavy, and about the size of an apple or maybe even 
slightly bigger.  Useful as a paperweight, I suppose.
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and charmingly drawn NPCs like a grumpy old tree trying to prevent you from
climbing him:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gametext rounded&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&quot;Hah!&quot;  says the tree.  &quot;That&#x27;ll teach you.&quot;  &quot;Ha!&quot;  you say back, grabbing the 
apple.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &quot;Oh,&quot; says the tree.  &quot;I hadn&#x27;t thought of that.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This changes later as the game&#x27;s tone grows more serious (again, much like 
Tolkien&#x27;s prose changed between &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the 
Rings&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;), but the entire game is beautifully written, with funny and 
compelling descriptions. The world it is set in seems like a condensed version 
of &lt;em&gt;Once and Future&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (which it pre-dates by several years, of course) 
sometimes, in that it is not a generic fantasy world but alive with strange 
beasts and vivid locations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One small critique must be permitted amid all the praise: the game suffers (not
much, though) from small oversights:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gametext rounded&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&amp;gt;PUT IT IN CAGE&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(You receive no message to the effect, but the action has worked). Later on,
there are a number of the TADS equivalent of &lt;code&gt;rtrue;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; missing, and
you&#x27;ll get the default response to an action displayed after Dan&#x27;s own, like 
here:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gametext rounded&quot;&gt;
        You grab hold of the glider bar and adjust your position on it.  You&#x27;re ready to 
fly!  Okay, you&#x27;re now wearing the hang-glider.
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this doesn&#x27;t really matter much, and you&#x27;d probably have to be a
programmer to realize these are oversights (but then again, maybe not).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I couldn&#x27;t resist throwing in part of one of my favourite funny 
descriptions of all time:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gametext rounded&quot;&gt;
        Well, if you&#x27;ve ever wondered what was going on, you seem to have found the 
place where whatever it is that is going on happens.
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game is also one of the very few to use TADS&#x27; file input&#x2F;output features
(the two others I can think of off the top of my head being &lt;em&gt;Losing Your 
Grip&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Lost New York&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;; I know I have forgotten at least one here).
The first time you start it, you will be asked a few questions, the answers
to which are stored in a configuration file so you won&#x27;t have to answer them
again until you delete it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing I don&#x27;t remember having seen in any other game are transitional
messages as you walk from location to location, things like&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gametext rounded&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&amp;gt;N&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You walk north, and soon arrive back at the open field.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One more thing of note: the game does not keep score in a traditional way. 
Instead, it divides solvable puzzles into major and minor tasks and tells you
how many of those you have achieved, then rates you according to that. Since
all major objects must be accomplished to win the game, SCORE can give you
an indication of how far along you are.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Note: just as I&#x27;m writing this, I&#x27;m reading through the help system again,
and notice it contains something akin to this paragraph. I didn&#x27;t steal it
from there, honestly!)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much for game mechanics - what is the game about? &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It begins harmlessly enough -- or, actually, it doesn&#x27;t as you quickly come
to realize. It seems an accident that you fall off a cliff, but something
rescues you -- bluesilver wings -- the Phoenix that gave the game part of its
name?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever it is, you are transported to a fantasy world and are left to explore.
It seems peaceful at first but, when you come across some mushrooms, things
change quickly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plot spoilers below -- mark the seemingly empty space with your mouse if you
want to see this. Lynx users: sorry.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;bordered&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;It seems _you_ are the phoenix -- or at least one of many phoenices placed
upon the Earth by a Fallen Angel to guard against an alien race known only as
_Them_, as they have no pronouncable name in any Earth language. They 
know that you are a threat, and They decided to kill you, but the Angel, 
Daniel, brought you to safety. Now the fate of humanity lies with you...&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The puzzles that are there are mostly logical, but some things will most likely
involve a fair amount of trial and error. There are plenty of clues given by 
the narrative itself -- either in the actual game text, or by NPCs (also in
the form of little notes left lying around) -- and the help menu also contains
several generic hints. Be sure to check it out after you win for a number of
fun things to try.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lethe Flow Phoenix&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is a medium-short game (though Dan seemed to think it
was too long for the first IF Competition), but that doesn&#x27;t make it any less
good. The only gripe I had with it is that it was over before I wanted it to
be over. Things are left unresolved, and while the ending certainly isn&#x27;t what
you would expect, I felt it was better that way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only thing that&#x27;s left to say to you is: play the best game ever:
&lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;plover.net&#x2F;%7Egschmidl&#x2F;speedif&#x2F;chef.gam&quot;&gt;You are a CHEF!&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, also
written by Dan Shiovitz, nominated for Best Writing in 2000&#x27;s XYZZY Awards.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other thing, left to say to Dan: write another game!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Getting a Grip on LYG</title>
        <author><name>Gunther Schmidl</name></author>
        <published>2001-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010316/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010316/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here Be Spoilers&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, naturally. Consider yourself warned.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stephen Granade&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;Losing Your Grip&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is (or, rather, &#x27;was&#x27;: registration is
no longer possible, and there is a free version forthcoming) one of the few 
shareware games in the IF world. And like most shareware IF, it was well worth
its price.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;LYG&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; game. It is divided into five fits and two 
interludes, some larger, some smaller, but it&#x27;ll take you quite a while to get 
through the game.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you read a hint request on one of the Interactive Fiction-related 
newsgroups, and you realize you can&#x27;t remember that happening in the game you
played. Surely this person got the game wrong?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They didn&#x27;t. Stephen sneakily made the game even larger -- and, thus, a lot more
replayable than it already is -- by sending you to one of two different versions
of a fit depending on small choices made in the fit before that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And he doesn&#x27;t do this once -- he does it twice. It&#x27;s pretty daring to include
multiple paths in a story given the danger nobody ever discovers them, but
he pulls it off beautifully. And the game is good enough you&#x27;ll want to go back
and try the alternative fits as well.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from being huge and sneaky, &lt;em&gt;LYG&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is also a difficult game, 
especially in the later fits. The game begins harmless enough:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gametext rounded&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Rain and mud.&lt;&#x2F;b&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those are your first solid memories.  Rain pouring down on your head, filling 
your eyes.  Mud beneath your feet, filling your shoes.  Other details slowly 
filter in.  The trees surrounding you.  The leaden skies above.  The chill wind 
cutting through your clothes with ease.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shelter would be a good beginning.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come to think of it, this isn&#x27;t harmless at all. Nevermind.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like in the commercially released (and horribly under-rated) graphic adventure 
game &lt;em&gt;Sanitarium&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Losing Your Grip&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is a bizarre journey through 
the depths of the subconscious that would make Freud go green with envy. This
is also where the similarities end -- almost. &lt;em&gt;LYG&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&#x27;s backstory is 
partially given away in the feelies you receive upon registration, and the game
makes a lot more sense with them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After an encounter with the now famous buried human head &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
you do manage to find shelter. And this is where things start to get really
strange.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an abandoned building full of stopped clocks; a person named Frankie, 
cataloguing spheres; objects that appear out of nowhere, containing -- what?
Memories? Threats?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your explorations soon yield a companion, a name-able dog who accompanies you on 
your further travels as well as being vital in solving puzzles. In fact, the 
first puzzle involving him (no gender is given, but I think of the dog as male) 
is not clued at all, as far as I can tell, and will probably involve having to 
restart for most players when they realize they can not carry objects across 
fits. This is, however, the only puzzle I really found &amp;quot;unfair&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;arbitrary&amp;quot; 
(in a sense) -- I may have needed to use hints continuously in the later fits 
(especially the Mathematical and the Abstract), but those puzzles were well 
enough clued to be solvable without resorting to the excellent in-game hints, 
given enough time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Did I mention hints are only available when you register? Don&#x27;t worry, the
forthcoming free version will probably provide them also.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very many things in this game are allegorical, and most do not reveal their
deeper meaning until a later Fit, if at all. Stephen deliberately does not 
explain his own designs; he fears that players will see his words as 
authoritative (which makes sense, him being the author and all) when he is much
more interested in what players think. &amp;quot;Yes, it&#x27;s deliberate,&amp;quot; as Zarf would 
say.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later fits take the player, Terry, into a hospital or his old school 
(depending), a fairy-tale world, an abstract or mathematical puzzle-fest
(again, depending) and finally to confrontation with his nemesis -- and 
himself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game is extremely well-written, the scenery pulling you right in. It 
understands a surprising number of commands. My favourite: after a doctor
had told me to &amp;quot;Administer CPR. Now,&amp;quot; I typed, without really thinking as the
situation was urgent, &lt;code&gt;ADMINISTER CPR&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, and lo! it worked. Excellent.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NPCs in the game respond to what they need to be able to respond to, and
not much more. That&#x27;s perfectly fine with me; I&#x27;ve never been a friend of 
talking to NPCs just to try and break mimesis. The only thing seeming a bit odd
is dialogue along the lines of:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gametext rounded&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&amp;gt;ASK FRANKIE ABOUT SPHERE&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frankie asks, &quot;Which sphere do you mean, the pile of spheres, or the light 
sphere?&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt;THE PILE OF SPHERES&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(etc.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This response feels (and is, of course) artificial. Again, I don&#x27;t care much;
gameplay is much more important, and this is where the game delivers. And 
delivers. And delivers. After I&#x27;d beaten the game the first time, I tried all
the possible alternative endings, which add so much more to the game. Then I
went back and replayed it for the other two fits right away. When I replayed
part of it for this review, I still liked it as much as the first time round.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that, my friends, is what counts in a game.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Note: If you want to know more about Losing Your Grip than you can possibly
imagine you want to, there was an interview on 
&lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;ifmud.port4000.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ifMud&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; with Stephen, the transcript 
of which you can find &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www-bioc.rice.edu&#x2F;%7Elpsmith&#x2F;IF&#x2F;bookclub&#x2F;grip&#x2F;interview.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those not in the know, Stephen implemented &lt;code&gt;KICK HEAD&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; as a verb.
Naturally, instead of trying to help the head, everyone kicked it instead. 
&lt;em&gt;[Ed. Note: This is untrue.  There are people who did try to help the head
first, and only tried to kick it after running out of other verbs to try.]&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
Moreover, this one thing is what the game became (in)famous for, though there
is so much more. Can&#x27;t have it all.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Smooching 101</title>
        <author><name>Jonathan Rosebaugh</name></author>
        <published>2001-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010302/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010302/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Spoilers: There are parts of this review that may spoil some parts of the game
for some people people. These parts are triple-rot13 encoded for your
protection.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a game has a property defined by (quality of game) &#x2F; (time it took to make),
then Pytho&#x27;s Mask has just beaten Shade&#x27;s record. It&#x27;s a bit rough around the
edges, but it&#x27;s much better than what you&#x27;d expect from a game that took only
one week to write, even from the master that is Emily Short. (Of course, I loved
her SpeedIF entry, as well.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot is what we&#x27;ve come to expect from Emily. Take something that&#x27;s embedded
in the background of our worldview, add a few twists, stir in a unique way of
looking at it, and let settle into IF form. Serves everyone. (Ok, the Rats of
NIMH ref in her SpeedIF entry is not quite as universal as Greek myth and
Platonism, but I still loved it.) In a world reminiscent of the Romantic
universe-picture, the earth and heavenly bodies influence events at court. The
Comet, which comes only once a century, shatters the balance, both in heaven and
on earth. This is the time when chaos can reign and those with a mind for dirty
politics can exert their will. (Reading Tillyard&#x27;s The Elizabethan World Picture
has really paid off.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The king has not been doing so well physically, and your Order (of which little
is shown save that it is a force for order and justice) wishes that he remain
capable of his office. The PC remains somewhat mysterious, though I believe that
most of this is due either to the author&#x27;s constrained schedule or my inability
to puzzle out some of the more badly coded parts. (Which are better than average
IF, even so.) Also mysterious, though with a greater reason, is the man who got
you an invitation to court on the Night of the Comet. He&#x27;s a Zorro-like figure
with a black mask. V trg gur srryvat gung gur snpg gung ur vf va snpg gur cevapr
vf fhccbfrq gb or zber boivbhf guna vg vf, gubhtu ntnva guvf znl or whfg zl onq
yhpx. And the fortune-teller provides a very nice confirmation of the mythology
of this world.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of characters, Emily has created another very nice conversation system.
It mixes the best parts of ASK&#x2F;TELL and menu-based conversation, though it
doesn&#x27;t always work quite right. It&#x27;s been explained in detail in other places,
so I won&#x27;t go into it here, but it&#x27;s really very good. I was sometimes left with
the feeling that my character had zoned out for a bit and missed some
conversation, but these few mimesis-shattering bugs are small, and can easily be
fixed in future versions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of character and plot, perhaps now is a good time to mention that
Pytho&#x27;s Mask was a SmoochieComp 2001 game, and as such it has not a little bit
of romance involved. Here Emily&#x27;s skill with multiple endings especially shines
through. You aren&#x27;t railroaded into any particular ending or relationship,
though like the rest of the time, sometimes the interactivity seems sparse. This
is, of course, the necessary side effect of a shortened development schedule.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok. Those of you who read my Galatea review may be asking, &amp;quot;Does it mean
anything?&amp;quot; to which I respond, &amp;quot;Doesn&#x27;t everything?&amp;quot; However, since answering
with a question fails to satisfy anyone but Socrates and Jesus, I&#x27;ll say this.
I&#x27;m not going to try to read deep things into this. Avril says that Soteria has
a part to play, and she&#x27;ll play it the way she&#x27;s supposed to, come hell or high
water, no matter what she does. This is not the way things actually are -- you
can do many different things, resulting in endings all along a spectrum. Still,
if she just sits back and lets the party unfold, nothing happens. This is mostly
just due to the way Emily implemented this game, i think, but it can still mean
something here. If you want to care. I like to think I do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked it. Will you? That depends. If you, as I do, think Emily is the best
thing since sliced cheese, (zarf and Adam Cadre are bread and salami,
respectively) by all means play this game. If you&#x27;d rather wait for a more
finished product, Emily has said that she&#x27;s planning to fix it up a bit and
release a version 2. Also, for budding IF authors, you should not try to write
your game a week before deadlines. But if you do, this is what you should aspire
to. I really liked this game. That&#x27;s a small catagory: Emily, zarf, and Adam
star regulary here, and a handful of other authors show up too. Ah, what the
heck. Just go play it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Care For Another?</title>
        <author><name>Emily Short</name></author>
        <published>2001-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010223/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010223/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Andrew Pontious&#x27; &lt;em&gt;Rematch&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is the Aisle of puzzle games: a single move 
is your window of opportunity to avert a negative outcome, which 
means you will have to replay again and again.  147 times, in my case.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some ways this is the ultimate timed puzzle, and I don&#x27;t always 
like timed puzzles.  &lt;em&gt;Change in the Weather&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, wonderful though it was 
in other respects, drove me just about nuts.  I survived the 
experience only with a walkthrough and laudanum.  Since &lt;em&gt;Rematch&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is 
just the one move, however, you don&#x27;t have a long sequence to replay 
only to fail.  The structure also enforces careful puzzle design: one 
common complaint about bad puzzles is that they don&#x27;t give enough 
feedback when you are close to, but have not yet arrived at, the 
solution.  In &lt;em&gt;Rematch&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, everything you can do necessarily produces 
some outcome, often an instructive one.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rematch&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; also accomplishes nicely a difficult task of IF recently 
discussed on rgif: encouraging the player to use non-standard verbs 
and syntax in order to accomplish game-specific goals.  There are a 
number of verbs in the game that fall outside the normal lexicon of 
IF games.  More to the point, however, Pontious has hacked the parser 
to accept much longer than normal input strings, with multiple 
indirect objects, for instance.  I wouldn&#x27;t have attempted these 
except that game play seemed to demand it; after my first few 
successes in this direction I had greater and greater faith in the 
game&#x27;s ability to understand the most outlandish sequences (and, in 
many cases, to have an interesting outcome for them.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This combines with the game&#x27;s other embedded hints to make for a 
forward-moving rather than stuck-and-frustrated play experience most 
of the time, and Pontious has also taken care to provide colorful or 
entertaining outcomes for verbs that aren&#x27;t immediately relevant to 
the puzzle, so that experimentation is rewarded.  Helpful also is the 
auto-undo command, which undoes your actions each time you fail.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one-turn format does also work against the puzzle, though -- or 
at least it did for me.  In order to reach a solution, you need to do 
a certain amount of exploration -- gathering information, but at the 
cost of losing over and over again.  This might have been less of an 
issue had the event-to-be-prevented been less horrific.  As it was I 
felt faintly guilty doing things that were not direct attempts at 
solution, and it wasn&#x27;t until I was actually told to explore more 
that I had the gumption to ignore the outcome and do so 
systematically.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approached with this systematic detachment, it&#x27;s a successful if 
somewhat evil puzzle.  I was confused when it was going on, then 
gradually had more and more of a sense of what I wanted to do; at the 
end, however, it all clicked together with a satisfying snap, leaving 
no loose ends.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As writing or story I think it is slightly less successful.  Even 
excellent descriptions and dialogue begin to pall on the 129th 
reading, and much of the NPC conversation has a somewhat stiff and 
unconvincing quality.  There is a good reason for this, 
gameplay-wise, but it lends strength to the impression, especially on 
repeated playings, that these are clockwork people carrying out their 
clockwork functions in a world where you alone are sentient.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mention this only because there is a story and characterization 
going on here: adumbrated in the opening words of the game is the 
relationship you have with the other characters, and the more you 
play the clearer the situation becomes.  It is significant not only 
from a puzzle point of view but also for the whole flavor of the 
game; but it never develops beyond a certain point, because the scope 
for development of complicated interrelationships is necessarily 
somewhat limited here.  Shallowly worked out, but thematically 
important.  My PC&#x27;s frustration with the unstoppable cycle of Fate 
(the puzzle, the disaster, which play out over and over again) 
mingles with his frustration over the interpersonal situation.  This 
far, I think, it is effective.  On the other hand, the aforementioned 
need to distance myself from the urgency of the puzzle distracts me 
from viewing the characters as characters and encourages the attitude 
that they are merely cogs in a complex interlocking gear system.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deeply moving narrative, then, it is not, partly because that is not 
its purpose (arguably) and partly because the puzzle goes to war with 
the story aspect and wins.  As a puzzle, though, it&#x27;s an entertaining 
and rewarding one.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>The Tale of the Reviewer</title>
        <author><name>Gunther Schmidl</name></author>
        <published>2001-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010216/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010216/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning: Here Be Spoilers&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. If you see a lot of white space between 
sentences, that means I&#x27;ve obscured part of the sentence to not give away 
things you might not want to know. Mark with your mouse to see the spoiler.
If you&#x27;re on Lynx, this won&#x27;t work. Sorry.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people know Andrew Plotkin, or Zarf, as he refers to himself, for the text
adventures he writes. Not too many know he has released an excellent puzzle 
story game (or &amp;quot;abstract fairy tale&amp;quot;, as Zarf describes it) called &lt;em&gt;System&#x27;s 
Twilight&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the reason for this might be that it was only ever released for the
Macintosh; another reason for people not playing it might have been that it was
distributed as shareware until little more than a year ago.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, with the advent of emulators like 
&lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;gamma.nic.fi&#x2F;%7Elpesonen&#x2F;BasiliskII&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Basilisk II&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and the
free availability of both MacOS 7.5.5 and 
&lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.eblong.com&#x2F;zarf&#x2F;twilight.html&quot;&gt;the game itself&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, there&#x27;s 
no more reason not to try it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first played the shareware version in 1999, finished what was there, then
registered to see the rest. And there&#x27;s a lot of game in there for a small
download like this.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;System&#x27;s Twilight&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is, first and foremost, a puzzle game. But not in the common
&amp;quot;Sliding Puzzle - Maze - Towers of Hanoi - repeat&amp;quot; sense; instead, it requires
you to plan logically, to think ahead, take notes and retry and retry and retry
until you succeed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sadistic Software is devoted to making your head hurt&amp;quot; say the credits, and
the game is good at that. While the first puzzles are (relatively) easy, 
requiring you to find and manipulate words, connect circuit boards, traverse
trees and duplicate patterns, they get a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; harder later on. Some are
so hard, in fact, that I was wondering how anyone could have solved them 
without the aid of the excellent Hint Guide.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will encounter many types of puzzles, and each branch on the map is usually
devoted to one or two types. There is everything from pattern matching to
Sokoban to puzzles I don&#x27;t even know a name for.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of them require a very good grasp of the English language (for example &lt;span class=&quot;bordered&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;knowing that &amp;quot;score&amp;quot; &#x2F; 10 = 2&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;). One of the word
puzzles is so fiendish that there is a hint for it in the &amp;quot;about&amp;quot; text and on
the web page. &amp;quot;This is the only puzzle in the game that I believe is too hard&amp;quot;
writes Zarf. I disagree :-)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the game is more than a puzzle-fest for the sake of itself. It also has a
story.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game plays in the &amp;quot;System&amp;quot;, an abstract computer-like world with data
streams, vaults, ruins, workshops and trees of the digital sort. You play &amp;quot;You&amp;quot;,
the protagonist of the game, who is intent on finding out why the System is
falling apart. On the way, you meet many interesting characters and try to
uncover their respective agendas. The ultimate goal is to bring stability back
to the System.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you finish each section, you are presented with a tale. All the tales and
names in the game tie heavily into voodoo and African folklore. Some of the 
names are explained when you finish the game; if you want a full list, check
out the aforementioned Hint Guide. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, you can&#x27;t finish an entire section in one go; there is usually a point
where you will get stuck and require an item that is to be found in another
part of the game. As you slowly unlock more and more of the game, you gain a
deeper understanding of what is behind the System&#x27;s problems and the various
schemes and plans of the supporting cast.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final puzzle is a masterpiece of evil, and has been widely discussed on the
Macintosh game newsgroups. It is fiendish and clever in almost the same way as
+=3 was. (If you&#x27;ve never heard of it, here&#x27;s a quick summary: you are 
inventoryless and a troll requires three items from you to let you pass. There
are no apparent things around, &lt;span class=&quot;bordered&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;and the solution is to 
take off your clothes and shoes and give those to him&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;. +=3 was a concept
game to get players to think out of the box; and this one is too, except that
it&#x27;s clued troughout the game.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which doesn&#x27;t mean I have ever seen somebody reach it and not ask for help.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few niggles: it&#x27;s not possible to replay a puzzle. &amp;quot;Yes, it should be. No,
I&#x27;m not touching the code again.&amp;quot; is the official reaction, and I say fair
enough. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ending screen, I just noticed, still mentions the registration 
sheet (which is available from the web page, but no longer necessary) and gives
Zarf&#x27;s old e-mail address, while the &amp;quot;about&amp;quot; text gives the new one.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What irked me was that the registration screen has been replaced with a 
&amp;quot;register somebody else&#x27;s software&amp;quot; reminder. Nice intention, but completely
out of place and annoying.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;System&#x27;s Twilight&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is a game in the tradition of Cliff Johnson&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;The Fool&#x27;s 
Errand&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;3 in Three&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I found it much more forgiving than &lt;em&gt;3 in 
Three&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (which I still haven&#x27;t solved and probably never will), but harder 
than &lt;em&gt;The Fool&#x27;s Errand&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. If you enjoyed any of those, or if you like hard 
puzzles, this is a game for you. Conversely, if you enjoyed this game, you will 
probably like the other two, but most likely not be able to find them anymore. 
Unless, that is, you look into abandonware sites, which is bad blah blah 
copyright blah blah who cares blah blah. If you&#x27;re more of the puzzle-less 
fraction, steer clear of this game. I played the game again for this review, and 
even though I was using the Hint Guide constantly to get through quickly, it 
still took me several hours to get through - first-time players will most likely 
be stumped for days, if not weeks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end of the game promises another game in the same style, to be named 
&lt;em&gt;Moondials&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I don&#x27;t know if it&#x27;s part of Murphy&#x27;s Law that any game announced
before it&#x27;s done will never be released (or very vary late), but I hope 
&lt;em&gt;Moondials&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; will be an exception.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How about it, Mr. Plotkin?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>An Undiminished Chord</title>
        <author><name>Emily Short</name></author>
        <published>2001-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010209/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010209/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Augmented Fourth&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is a fairly easy puzzle romp whose appeal lies in
wackily charming worldbuilding and sly jokes&#x2F;reworkings of classic IF
and fantasy tropes. It&#x27;s well-crafted and polished (going to show,
perhaps, that there&#x27;s no reason an author&#x27;s first-ever release can&#x27;t
be competently assembled) and I encountered no bugs.  It did,
however, have some irritating patches, mostly related to the design
of the puzzles.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Augmented Fourth&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; uses an adapted-for-its-genre version of the
Enchanter spellcasting concept: as a trumpeter you can play pieces
whose magical power work transformations on your environment.  And
like the Enchanter spells, these pieces must be painstakingly
acquired and learned (though, fortunately, Uri has dispensed with the
irritating requirement that one learn them over and over again.  Once
you&#x27;ve learned a piece you know it; musicians are apparently less
absentminded than magicians, as a rule.)  This is a fun system in its
basic concept, and one reason it has been reused so many times over
the years, I imagine, is that it permits the author to put
considerable freedom into the hands of the player.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are, of course, a couple of possible downsides.  One is the
combinatorial problem: you can trust that your players will try the
spell in just about every conceivable situation, not only in the one
or two places where it will solve a puzzle but in all the others,
including several where it ought to cause major trouble.  Uri does a
good job of providing interesting failure messages where the spells
are not going to work; he is also aided by the fact that the
music-spells are not directable, so instead of having to implement an
interaction (or failure) for every game object, he only has to deal
with every location.  This, I can only imagine, made things a lot
simpler.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other downside is that the spells themselves do fairly odd and
abstract things.  This is delightful when it works; when it doesn&#x27;t,
one is often left wondering what&#x27;s missing and whether one is even
trying the right thing.  In one sequence of the game in particular I
was most of the way to the correct solution, but kept failing because
I hadn&#x27;t set things up quite properly.  I had the idea; I just didn&#x27;t
have the execution exactly as Uri envisioned it, and there were no
&amp;quot;you&#x27;re almost right&amp;quot; messages to help me along, so I was left to
wonder whether I had the right spell at all.  Making this even more
frustrating is that the spells fail randomly, especially during the
early section of the game; you can easily &#x27;misplay&#x27; a piece, not
because it&#x27;s not the right piece for the moment but because the
random number generator is not on your side.  This, boys and girls,
is frustrating.  I suppose the idea is to convey the feeling of
accomplishment as the game goes on and you become a more proficient
musician, able to play correctly the first time, but it also makes
the early puzzles a pain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much for that: there were a couple of spots where I was held up by
what I felt was an arbitrary lack of hintage, and insufficient
indication when I was close.  There were also red herrings (besides
the obvious one), some of them (to me at least) moderately confusing.
On the whole, however, I didn&#x27;t find this to be too severe a problem.
The author provides an elegantly implemented walkthrough too,
available from gmd, htmlized so that you can highlight only the parts
you want to see.  This is nice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This game also pointed up some spots in which my expectations have
changed since early text adventure games.  &lt;em&gt;Augmented Fourth&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; does some
things the Old Skool way.  The need to do arbitrary things just
because they seem like they might be a good idea.  The freedom to
mistreat NPCs, which, these days, makes me feel a little guilty.  The
linearity of the game design, a lot of which consists of getting into
one place which contains a key to another place where there&#x27;s a key
to a third place...  Then, too, I nearly ran screaming when I
encountered the, ah, maze.  Not to worry, though: it&#x27;s not as bad as
it looks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it all ends well: the endgame is satisfying and not too
difficult, which is How It Should Be.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are moments of surrealism in the game, and plays on the names
of things reminiscent of the un-un-machine, the T-remover, and other
such mechanisms of text-only adventures.  There is much talk these
days of simulationist IF, of achieving &amp;quot;immersion&amp;quot; by getting the
player to identify as strongly as possible with the PC; &lt;em&gt;Augmented
Fourth&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; pursues a different direction, never trying to pull the player
in but keeping much of the amusement value of the game precisely at
that interface between player and player character.  I think I
derived as much amusement from the score notification system as I did
from some of the puzzles.  At the same time, there is a consistent
story providing context for all this -- which the player also
receives in an unimmersive way, by receiving flashes of what is
happening &amp;quot;meanwhile&amp;quot; in another part of the kingdom.  The result is
stylish and entertaining, even if not emotionally compelling
particularly; I never felt suspense or was particularly concerned
about the jeopardy of my PC, for instance.  But that was, in this
case, fine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;em&gt;Augmented Fourth&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; shines most is in the goofy style, which, with
its numerous animals and brightly colored objects, frequently
reminded me of a children&#x27;s book.  Combined with the relative
easiness and the elegant implementation (which deals nicely with book
objects and other tricky items), this makes it a pleasant way to
spend a few hours.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Deus Ex Machine</title>
        <author><name>Sam Kabo Ashwell</name></author>
        <published>2001-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010202/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010202/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first thing you notice about BAD_MACHINE is that everything looks like code. (There&#x27;s a suggestion, almost
certainly intentional, that something&#x27;s wrong with your game file, a nice touch that also suggests
machine-empathy and eases the transition to thinking like a machine a little). The basic outline: you play a
robot, Mover #005, whose normal mindless existence as a worker for an entity called the Warehouse is disrupted
by an unspecified disaster. The damage caused to him not only disrupts various of his settings and his
delivery of code (much of the code appears corrupt) but to achieve... sentience? Motive? Independence? Whatever
it may be, it earns him the title of Bad_Machine (fully functional CPUs are referred to as Good_Machine) and
brings him under the threat of destruction or reprogramming by minions of the omnipresent Warehouse. It&#x27;s a
very dark piece, but only you realize it is: 005 is too restricted by his code and immersed in the Warehouse
to realize the tragedy and pathos of his story.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BAD_MACHINE would really, really confuse a first-time IF player. And it helps one hell of a lot if you&#x27;re
familiar with writing code of some sort because so much of the important information is in code or uses
code-like syntax. This feels, at first, like a blend between wilful anti-verbosity and artistic experiment.
Certainly, games have been written that play around with the relationship between player, parser, and
protagonist (LASH, Resident) and with freedom-of-robots themes (LASH, Galatea, Delusions) but never, to my
knowledge, anything quite this extreme. (In other media, the first things I thought of were the enslaved
robots of I, Robot and the machine-mind of RoboRally). There&#x27;s a definite feel for the medium: unlike much of
IF, Bmch would be completely impractical if transferred to literature, film or other narrative media. And I
can imagine how much work must have gone into rewriting the basic library to achieve this effect.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technique has a lot of force at times, and capably turns the weaknesses of IF to its advantage. The
robot&#x27;s confusion at achieving sentience(?) is mirrored by the player&#x27;s confusion at having to operate in
code: the difficulty in moving and examining things add to the apparent inevitability of 005&#x27;s fate: 005 has
only just gained sentience(?), he is (like the player) being pursued in a bizarre place by an omniescent,
omnipresent faceless enemy. The irony is that only the player gets the feeling of fear and dread: 005 is
unable to express or produce it. This is indicative of the different way the player and 005 see the game: even
though we are more unfamiliar with the meaning of the code, we can assess its import.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disquieting presence of even more enslaved robots than 005 around him, following endlessly repeating loops
until they fall apart, is another IF weakness turned to an advantage. The author acknowledges his debt to
imagery of group insects, and it shows in the sorts of robots defined: the robots do not repower from plugs
but from an Energizer, and other classes of robot (drone, worker, assaulter, queen) show this too. The story
thus possibly owes a debt, indirectly, to various works based on ant or bee-based literature (Ursula K. Le
Guin&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;The Compass Rose&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, the ant sequences in the &lt;em&gt;Once and Future King&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;), as well as to Asimov&#x27;s Robot stories;
though, of course, it&#x27;s hard to be sure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feeling of fear and pursuit was, as I played it, only apparent after starting the game again after losing
for the first time (another nice touch: no &amp;quot;You have lost&amp;quot; type message if you get repaired or destroyed, the
code says it all): the first time I was captured by other automata, I felt (whether the writer was aware of
this or not I don&#x27;t know) a feeling of hope (I&#x27;m going to be repaired, then I can be told my real mission!)
combined with an underlying anxiety (no you&#x27;re not, your head&#x27;s being bolted back on and back to work you go).
Once you&#x27;ve worked out what&#x27;ll kill you and what&#x27;ll keep you safe, this fades a little, which is a shame.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of pure pleasure at playing, I must admit that, while there were a few good points, the game was
overall quite hard work. Perhaps it&#x27;s because I principally enjoy IF for the literary aspect: plot, dialogue,
description, atmosphere, themes. As far as the first three go, there isn&#x27;t a great deal (although I think it
was Camus who coined the immortal phrase &amp;quot;probabilistic anti-awareness test dumping memory full-on
{i:=0;fornext(while(true)attempt clear() clear() clear() opening return;breakput_up*this-&amp;gt;self_referential
opening() live-syscall()&amp;quot;) but there is more of the latter two in Bmch than I would have expected-- and,
bucking the trend for IF that plays about with the parser this much, contains no in-joke I could find apart
from the obligatory xyzzy, and is in no way self-referential. And, unlike most games which are
description-light, I found myself coming back to Bmch.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine is also, as far as the essential nature of puzzles is involved, fairly standard: find solution to
puzzle, progress to next puzzle. This is made a little more difficult by the alien nature of the robot&#x27;s modus
operandi: to a certain extent, standard IF techniques of play have to be abandoned: while this is a tough
process, it gives Machine a powerful individual character, and helps give the player a level of empathy with
the way 005 thinks. For example, in terms of getting information, indexing is almost invariably superior to
examining. (You can, however, do an interesting variant of VERBOSE by setting your awareness to high: this
increases, principally, how much you notice of the communications of other robots. Verbosity&#x2F;awareness levels
are, perhaps, an underused narrative tool; the extent Machine uses this could, potentially, lead to
experimental (though perhaps more conventional in other ways than Machine) work with even greater use of
varying awareness levels.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danger levels are quite high, and you are likely to &amp;quot;die&amp;quot; quite a lot, and often, frustratingly, as the result
of previous actions. (Save). And the low verbosity could, possibly, allow you to solve or partially solve
puzzles without realizing it (though, all things considered, this is unlikely); in most IF, when you complete
a puzzle, you get rewarded by a bit of text informing you of your success-- there can be no slap on the back
for the robot and, because of the low level of description, it can be uncertain whether an action is the result
of your actions or would have happened anyway; while this adds to the unfamiliar, bizarre effect of the game,
it certainly makes it more difficult to play; the fact that objects or machines are only identified by
function and only rarely by form can make it difficult to visualize a situation and thus to mentally
manipulate it. Whether this is was a concious decision or not, I don&#x27;t know: it fits the context, but does
remove an element of pleasure from gameplay. That said, I&#x27;m not sure if Machine is meant to be pleasurable.
All that IF needs to be good IF is to elicit a response, and Machine certainly does that, if only by the
wierding out at the start.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game bravely breaks away from the standard IF verbs-you-always-need: though EXAMINE and SEARCH are still
there, they are often next to useless: the floor is also taken from under your feet by the uncertanity of the
data you see, particuarly with regard to movement. Initially, you&#x27;re unsure (and does it matter?) whether the
data on possible exits is erroneous or if your legs are responding badly to commands, which adds a nice
element of existentialist doubt to the already fairly unfamiliar (and thus unnerving) environment. I was
almost disappointed when I worked out the significance of the internal compass: the image of a robot stumbling
about, knowing what he perceives is faulty and trying hopelessly to correct it, works excellently.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The atmosphere can be broken up a bit, contrarily, by the introduction of things that would be regarded as
good practise in normal IF: anything randomized, for example, detracts somewhat from the mind-of-the-machine
effect, as in many of the results-of-action statements. &amp;quot;Wait&amp;quot;, for example, returns different &amp;quot;Time
passes&amp;quot;-type messages. The machine may be broken, but different code replies to identical actions in identical
situations, and, for a machine, this feels incongruous.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as you get a purpose of any sort and start puzzlesolving, at what ever level, the atmosphere changes a
bit, whether intentionally or not: you&#x27;re no longer a little confused robot menaced by a gigantic evil
machine, and you start to question motive a bit: what exactly are you trying to do and why? (This makes
puzzlesolving difficult: what are you trying to achieve, exactly?)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the release notes, the game might not work on some MaxTADS, HTML-TADS or Mac interpreters. It
worked fine on my Mac HTML-TADS, though with a few &amp;quot;undo&amp;quot; bugs, but don&#x27;t take my word for it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time limits: the trickiest question in IF. The timing in Bmch can seem punitive early on, when you&#x27;re not sure
what&#x27;s causing the drones to attack you; while this adds to the sinister efficient-machine image, it can be a
bit frustrating until you work out how to dodge the little buggers. Once that&#x27;s done, urgency is also imposed
by the need for energy: once you&#x27;ve refilled once, though, you&#x27;re unlikely to need it again, which is a mercy
(it&#x27;d get irritating if you had to chase down the energizer every twenty turns or so).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s some very nice, subtle humour undercurrent, such as when you attempt to take debris: &amp;quot;Debris is
debris. If (debris.use &amp;gt; 0), debris != debris.&amp;quot; The humour is, however, both quite sparse and solely percieved
by the audience, not 005, and thus does not really break up the sinister, inhuman atmosphere of Bmch.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finishing Bad Machine is tough. Wisely, the author has included sections of factory that are physically
accessible but which are guarded; this suggests the implied vast size of the Warehouse well, but can also lead
to red herrings. The solution is deceptively easy, at the end, and the success message is beautifully
understated. Which cuts two ways: it accurately reflects 005&#x27;s continuing incomprehension, but is very
anticlimatic; the power of anticlimax should not be underestimated, however.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most powerful image, though, is that of the sinister, faceless Machine&#x2F;Warehouse. The failure message is
beautifully sinister. Beautifully sinister. So sinister, in fact, that it feels a great deal preferable to be
hammered to death by a lifter. It&#x27;s nicely ironic that Mover 005 is Bad, while all the mindless automata
around it are Good; Bad Machine is, intentionally or not, reminiscent of oppressive regimes, transforming the
Fixer into a sinister Re-Education phychiatrist, the drones to gulag guards. 005&#x27;s complete inability to
disobey or fight against them (unWAREHOUSE) is both a realistic rationale for not being able to actions that
would appear physically possible, and a pointer, via other IF, to ourselves: how different is 005&#x27;s
&amp;quot;unWAREHOUSE&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;action IS futile&#x2F;stupid&amp;quot; to Varicella&#x27;s various hangups, Lisa Flint&#x27;s refusal to kill, or
&amp;quot;Real adventurers don&#x27;t use such language&amp;quot;-- Which, since these are all realstic reasons for human inability to
act, points the finger on to reality, and the questions of compulsion, free will and liberty of
spontenaity-- are we masters of our own minds, or as much a repressed, trapped product of society as 005 is of
the Warehouse? As with life, Bad_Machine seems to have no apparent motive: the only alternative to producing
Product (unidentified, which is a superb touch: (action IS futile&#x2F;stupid) comes to mind) is subversiveness,
deception and destructiveness.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, Bad Machine is excellent, most so not for the code-speak, the puzzles, or the plot (such as it is)
but for it&#x27;s message: 005&#x27;s escape is purely symbolic, (after all, it&#x27;s going to run out of power soon enough)
but this does not detract from the power of the piece. The ending is satisfying without feelgood shmaltz, but,
for me at least, its true strength lay in its suggestion of dark, oppressive control, and in the futile but
necessary struggle against it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Dreams, Hubris, and Getting Away with Both</title>
        <author><name>Jonathan Rosebaugh</name></author>
        <published>2001-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010126/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010126/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that it was first released in the IF Art Show, not in a normal
IF competition, &lt;em&gt;Galatea&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; has a plot or, rather, a couple dozen plots. Like
its sister work, &lt;em&gt;Metamorphoses&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Galatea&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is an example of Multilinear IF, and a
very good one at that. Both &lt;em&gt;Galatea&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Metamorphoses&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; are intended, if I
understand the author correctly, to demonstrate ideal simulationist design, but
they are much more than demos.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Galatea&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is the first work since &lt;em&gt;So Far&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Photopia&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to take me prisoner, to
capture my heart. &lt;em&gt;So Far&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; did it with its marvelous worlds and sheer mystery,
&lt;em&gt;Photopia&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; did it when the pieces finally tumbled together, and &lt;em&gt;Galatea&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; does it,
well, with Galatea. I should explain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work begins with you, an art critic, standing in a forgotten corner of an
exhibition with Galatea. She is a statue, standing on a pedestal. She greets
you and, from there on, the plot is different for everyone. Emily Short has
written forty-odd endings, each of which can be reached in myriads of ways.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of one possible conversation, it is revealed that the
exhibition is a place where makers of artificial intelligences will show their
skill and, one possible ending (which I found only using txd, when I was
looking for something else) shows Galatea as one of the computerized creations.
I never found how to get it in the game. I didn&#x27;t want to -- this type of
ending I did not seek out. Fortunately, there are many endings that are not like
that. I could choose. And because I could, I chose the paths that made Galatea
a person, if not a human. I chose the paths that showed her her humanity, her
freedom.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? Because I could. Because it was the decent thing to do. Because, absurd to
even think it, I had fallen in love with her. By that time, I had forgotten
the existence of Emily Short, of my computer, of the game. Absurd, I say. And
so it is. I was worse than Gatsby! Understandable, perhaps. The point of this
work is to show the power of realistic NPCs in realistic games. That, it does.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why did the author write so many possible endings? Why did she open the door
for a naïve teenager to anthropomorphize? Why did she give some responsibility
for writing the story to the &lt;em&gt;player&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;?
Upon reading some essays from the author&#x27;s site, an answer appears. Ironically
enough, she did it because of me and because of everyone else that plays the game.
The aim is to give the freedom to do anything that is reasonable (reasonable in the game
world, I mean), to give the ability to have the game
respond to the player&#x27;s wishes. That is, she did it because she could.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this happens, it means that the player has an active role in the act of
creation. What we make may well be a judge of what we are. I am reminded of the
concept that arose around the time quantum mechanics was first becoming
well-known. It arose from the fact that the observer was an integral part of
the experiment and said, basically, that &amp;quot;wishing makes it so&amp;quot;. This also led
to some interesting interpretations of Schrödinger&#x27;s Cat, but I digress. The
author has written one scenario which she calls Eliza, where the PC bares his
soul for Galatea, but the game itself serves as a psychiatrist, forcing us to
see and try to understand some of what we are.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what do I make of Galatea? What stories have I decided to form? Good
question. I don&#x27;t know. There are endings such as the ones with Dionysus that
leave me fearful, but wanting to follow. There are endings that are happy,
endings that are not. I have brought her into mortality, or followed her to
immortality. I remain cautious. I -- again, the absurd, perhaps justifiable
response -- want to help her be.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&#x27;t. She&#x27;s a quarter-megabyte bit of code in my computer. The only
existence she has is inside my mind and the minds of everyone else who plays
the game. I can&#x27;t affect what they do with her; She&#x27;s not real &lt;em&gt;dammit!&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; I
overreact. I anthropomorphize. A good sense of fantasy is healthy, but when you
can&#x27;t tell the difference anymore, that&#x27;s insanity. Madness.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#x27;s in the game, too. Madness, given by the gods. Hubris, sometimes
punished, sometimes rewarded. For what is the idea of art, if not an intrusion
on the gods&#x27; monopoly on creation?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let&#x27;s turn the tables about and become somewhat paranoid for a moment.
I remember a certain ending: Galatea as daemon, or god. I remember that no one
has actually seen Pygmalion, we have only Galatea&#x27;s word for his existence. I
remember something Emily Short wrote, in a different context that suddenly
seems much too similar: &amp;quot;Greek myth is full of such moments, when a god among mortals,
disguised and mocked, suddenly turns with eyes shining. Terror follows, and
madness.&amp;quot; This certainly can explain almost all of the possible endings, if one
has a taste for such an idea. I don&#x27;t; it&#x27;s way too frightening. This is the
sort of time that I reassure myself that it&#x27;s only a game, and maybe half
succeed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we continue this sort of mind exercise, we come presently to Platonism and
again to quantum mechanics. If everything we perceive is but a shadow of some
higher plane, and everything that is, is only in the mind, then we can affect
reality directly, as opposed to the sort of everyday changes we make to the
world. Here we drift dangerously into semantics and religion, but it&#x27;s worth
taking a look at, anyhow.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so perhaps we have a trinity collaborating on this work: the Author, the
Reader, and the Subject, Galatea. We affect her by what we choose to write and
what we choose to read, but she affects us too, when we see what story we have
written and ponder what it can mean.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In closing, just in case you&#x27;re still with me, (as opposed to having quit
halfway through to download Galatea) I&#x27;d like to say one thing: Play this game.
Then, write your own. Pour your heart and soul into it. Cast it upon the
waters, and you may indeed receive it back a hundredfold.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>In a Most Curious Mantle</title>
        <author><name>Dan Shiovitz</name></author>
        <published>2001-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010119/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010119/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s not saying anything new to talk about the IF community having
mixed feelings about puzzles in games. Some people like, some people
don&#x27;t, and so on for pages. Games fall in various points on the
puzzleness spectrum: to one extreme you have things like
&lt;em&gt;Photopia&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;; and to the other,
things like &lt;em&gt;Mulldoon&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Heroine&#x27;s Mantle&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. The thing is,
while nobody would argue that
&lt;em&gt;Photopia&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&#x27;s success can be
explained entirely by its lack of puzzles (and not, you know, by
writing quality) far too many people make the mistake of thinking that
games like &lt;em&gt;Heroine&#x27;s Mantle&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; are successful entirely because
they have a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of puzzles. In fact, because these games are, or
appear to be, purely puzzle-centric, there&#x27;s been a massive lack of
critical attention to anything else about them. This is a
pity, because &lt;em&gt;Heroine&#x27;s Mantle&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is a world-class game that is
totally worthy of standing alongside &lt;em&gt;So Far&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; or
&lt;em&gt;Galatea&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in the category of
games that not only bust open new ground and reveal strange vistas,
they&#x27;re &lt;em&gt;good&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andy Phillips is of course no stranger to the IF world; before this
game he had previously come out with &lt;em&gt;Time: All Things Come To An
End&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Heist&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Enemies&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (four large games is enough to
make him noteworthy if only for sheer quantity). &lt;em&gt;Heroine&#x27;s Mantle&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
carries out almost every trend raised by his previous games (except,
thankfully, the grammatical errors, which are toned down considerably)
and molds them together into a game that, for the first time for
Phillips, feels complete and well-structured, and carries its story
with confidence.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what happens in the first twenty points or so of &lt;em&gt;Heroine&#x27;s
Mantle&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;: you are saved from drowning by a superheroine, you grow
up, you sneak into an office building, you attend a party, you find
out the world is threatened by a master criminal, you have an
encounter with a female assassin, you force your way to the penthouse,
you re-encounter the assassin in the middle of one of her nefarious
schemes, you battle some elite bodyguards, you hack a computer, you
ransack an office. Point-wise, this has all happened in just the first
five percent of the game. Later in the game, you battle various
super-villains (including a space-pirate), fight untold number of
robots and secret cultists, save the city from being poisoned, save
the mayor from being assassinated, and this is &lt;em&gt;all in the same
game&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Nobody else has done this or, really, anything close.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make this massive storyline go requires the player to make mental
leap after mental leap, often blindly, hoping the game will be there
when you land. There are machines that have to be fiddled with for no
other reason than that they&#x27;re there, capabilities of your ship that
have to be guessed at because they&#x27;re not fully explained anywhere,
even actions that have to be taken for no apparent reason other than
that, in retrospect, they look good. And people &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; this.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I obviously can&#x27;t tell people not to hate that in a game, but I can
say that you should be understanding this as a baseline axiom, not as
a flaw. Meyer Schapiro has this thing about the importance of a
the frame in doing criticism of a painting: it tells you where to
stop looking (and, thus, where to start).
&lt;em&gt;Galatea&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is set in a single
room, with a single NPC, with no takeable items. This is not a failure
of the game or a problem with the design. It&#x27;s the frame of the painting
that tells you &amp;quot;this is what I&#x27;m interested in; this is what to focus
on&amp;quot;. All IF has restrictions: from the parser, from the world model,
from our inability to code NPCs that can hold &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; conversation. And
the best games take these restrictions and deal with them, whether
it&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;Galatea&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
with the tiny world that focuses you on the single NPC,
&lt;em&gt;Spider &amp;amp; Web&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; with the restricted conversation options that
lead to a tense and weighty dialogue, or &lt;em&gt;Heroine&#x27;s Mantle&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; with
the forced actions and crazy puzzles that let Phillips create a huge
and glorious storyline.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should perhaps say a few more words about the superhero genre
that the game belongs to. Up till now, there was a distinct lack of
superhero games in IF. Some good ones have been written: &lt;em&gt;Hero,
Inc&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and the two &lt;em&gt;Frenetic Five&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; games, for instance, but the
most successful have all been comedies. Some part of the superhero
concept is indeed comedic, but mostly it isn&#x27;t, and we&#x27;ve been waiting
for a game that could capture the whole spirit of the superhero genre.
&lt;em&gt;Heroine&#x27;s Mantle&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; succeeds. It has humorous, even silly,
bits: wacky villains with strange motivations, ridiculous traps, and goofy
innocent citizens who talk to and&#x2F;or hinder you. But it also captures
the larger-than-life, super-good against super-evil,
fate-of-the-world-depends-on-this feeling that is so necessary for
realizing the promise of the genre.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most games have failed because
they&#x27;re too timid; Phillips dares to go farther and drags the player
along with him, willingly or not. Even the puzzles add to the feeling
of the titanic struggle -- there I am, 2am, grappling with the game, a
few cryptic hints, two megabytes of txd output, and &lt;em&gt;I&#x27;m still
stuck&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Meanwhile, the PC is engaged in a duel to the death with
the space pirate on the bridge of the submarine while trying to figure
out how the hell she can also divert the torpedoes from an ocean liner
full of innocent lives. You want &amp;quot;complicity&amp;quot;? It&#x27;s all here.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For certain sorts of games, the best reaction you can have as a player
is &amp;quot;I want to do something like that!&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;Heroine&#x27;s Mantle&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is
doing so many new and crazy things in so many areas that there are
dozens of possibilities that fly out in all directions. And what I&#x27;d
most like to see is for lots and lots of players to grab a walkthrough
or txd (or nothing at all besides the .z8, depending on how much
patience they have), play this, and then go out and write some games
of their own.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Eyeing the LASH</title>
        <author><name>James Mitchelhill</name></author>
        <published>2001-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010112/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010112/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The word &#x27;robot&#x27;, as is known by many SF fans, is derived from the Czech word
&#x27;robota&#x27;, meaning &#x27;forced labor&#x27; and was first used in the play R.U.R. by the
playwright Capek. LASH, by Paul O&#x27;Brian concerns a robot named the MULE
(Multiple Use Land Explorer), and its involvement in a guided salvage
operation on the lands of a former cotton plantation in what once was Georgia.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon opening LASH, we&#x27;re presented with the options to CONNECT or receive
HELP. This is one game where the HELP is essential reading. This is because the
HELP is not for the game itself, but for the robot that we are controlling. We
also get essential back-story in this section, everything you would expect if
you were in control of a remote salvage operation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, LASH looks like a superior treasure-hunt. Not a cave crawl, but
an after-apocalypse, burnt Earth crawl. That game might be interesting, but
it&#x27;s not LASH. Or at least, not after the first half-hour or so. After that
point, LASH becomes a much more complex game, the IF Literature fans get even
more interested and those who wanted a new Adventure kick their computer in
dismay.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If LASH has a greatest flaw, then it is this initial misleading. This is also
its greatest strength, despite the possibly that the initial premise will be
enough to persuade literature-seekers that LASH is a puzzler.  Regardless, this
is a very literate game. Half SF, half Family Saga, and half fable; which makes
LASH a game and a half, which is accurate. There&#x27;s a lot crammed into its z8
frame.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LASH&#x27;s best quality, though, is the writing. O&#x27;Brian&#x27;s descriptions are
evocative and suspenseful. Most impressive are the small details that the MULE
reports: Unsettling sounds in the distance; the strength of the wind, the
scratches on the wall; little hints at what has happened. The plantation the
robot visits is a place that has been, not one that is. The only criticism I
can make is that the background documents seem like they could have used a
little more work -- the tone seems slightly off. However, in the game proper,
the writing is among the best in interactive fiction.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the coding lives up to the writing&#x27;s promise. Although the initial
public release had a few bugs -- unsurprising given the scope of the game -- I
could only find bugs by actively seeking them. Given the impressive record of
maintenance, I&#x27;m sure that any bugs reported will be fixed when the author has
time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With its lack of any difficult puzzles, and the optional nature of most (I
played through it without a walkthrough, a rare experience for me), LASH is an
excellent introductory work, although not for children, due to the themes and
language the game is concerned with. The warning in the HELP section should be
taken seriously, even though it&#x27;s fictional presentation could obscure its
real purpose.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although LASH is not a game that will suit everybody, it does deserve to be
played. It is deep, and multiple play-throughs are rewarding. LASH can be an
extremely enjoyable and insightful experience. This is, quite simply, a
must-play game.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also deserves a closer look. If you haven&#x27;t played LASH yet, do so before
reading further: Spoilers will abound.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;spoilers&quot;&gt;SPOILERS&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LASH is a very complex game. Structurally, it is divided into three sections,
the framing story surrounding the dream of slavery. It also deals with three
eras. The MULE is resident to the time after the second American civil war,
and directly experiences the time before the first American civil war. The
player also reads of the time before the second civil war via Dr. Lisa Percy&#x27;s
diary. LASH also concerns itself with many themes -- slavery, war and race are
all readily apparent. Slavery is given primary attention, and this is perhaps
a mistake -- much criticism has been levelled at the game for its
simplification of the issue. &amp;quot;Slavery is bad,&amp;quot; the game says, to which the
player replies &amp;quot;I know.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, in this review, I won&#x27;t focus on the slavery issue. What seems more
important in the game, is the treatment of people; no-one in the game is what
they seem.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me justify that statement: Master Nicholas is revealed as Linda&#x27;s father
and (consequently) his son, Matthew, as Linda&#x27;s half-brother. Momma, the wholly
domestic slave, is revealed to have connections to the underground railroad.
Luke, Linda&#x27;s purported father, who attempted to murder Master Nicholas, was
doing so out of anger at the rape of Momma. Most interesting are the enforced
character changes. Linda must escape or be killed for the MULE to leave the
simulation. The Mule itself, is revealed to have the capability of sentience.
Every character -- potentially even the PC -- develops during LASH.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One consequence of this development, is that there&#x27;s a lot going on, and the
player can easily miss all the subtlety occurring around them. Another problem
is that a player might never get all this information. Some of it relies on
asking the right questions of Matthew with a limited number of moves. Other
information is only received if Nicholas attempts to rape Linda -- she can die
before this point, or he can sell her down the river. Of course, the
incompleteness of information leads to a high replayability value, as do the
multiple endings available. This is a balance between story and game, and a
consequence of the medium of IF.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also of interest is the race issue. As Linda is mixed-race, the MULE is part
machine, part human. Obvious comparisons can be drawn. Until we find out that
Nicholas is Linda&#x27;s father we assume she is wholly black and, until the MULE
enters the simulation, we treat it as completely inhuman. The appearances of
both Linda and the MULE remain unchanged after we learn of their true natures.
This can be taken as commentary about how people are treated based on what we
can see, and although that&#x27;s hardly a new idea, here we have an active and
deep relationship with the two oppressed protagonists. This is something that
could not have been achieved with static fiction. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also have Dr. Percy&#x27;s journal, which tells us that the second civil war was
fought over racial issues. The journal itself is a clever tool to prevent the
player from entering the simulation without first having learned this. O&#x27;Brian
has made this information required reading before we go back to the days of
slavery. The player must know that everything that was fought for in those
days, by Matthew and his Harvard friends, was futile. Everyone dies anyway, a
few generations on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, the journal is interesting in the way it reveals the Percys&#x27;
race. We&#x27;re not informed that they are black until we&#x27;re half-way through
Lisa&#x27;s diary. I suspect that, up until this point, a lot of players (myself
included) had assumed that they were white. That doesn&#x27;t make us racists
(although assuming that a criminal was black would), but it does give rise to
the question on a personal level -- if we make those assumptions, what other
assumptions do we make that we haven&#x27;t yet realized?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another facet of the game is how it explores the relationship between player
and protagonist. The MULE interface is used to justify the limited ways in
which an IF player can control the protagonist of a story. Various IF
conventions are incorporated into the game itself via careful design of the
MULE technology. Moreover, the story itself mimics classic IF -- the
treasure-hunt is the original text adventure plot. Even the nameless
adventurer is recreated here: You are the hero.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s this link to the past that highlights how far IF has come since those
not-so-distant origins. LASH is evolved IF on equal footing with print
literature, able to stand amongst the written works of the world and not be
found wanting. As I said earlier, LASH is a must-play game. In the future, if
IF is studied in colleges then LASH is the kind of historically significant
work that I hope will be on thier required playing lists. Paul O&#x27;Brian has
taken IF a step forward towards those days.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Don&#x27;t Go Violent On This Review</title>
        <author><name>Jonathan Blask</name></author>
        <published>2001-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2001-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <link href="https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010105/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://mjmusante.github.io/if-review/reviews/20010105/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of text games already being forgotten, despite the fact that
they&#x27;re available from our lovable IF archive and all of its incorrigibly wacky
mirrors.  I mean, who plays gems like Cosmoserve these days?  Not many, I&#x27;d
think, and for every Cosmoserve, there&#x27;s a dozen games that never made any sort
of impact on the IF community in any way.  These games are snapshots in time.
We play them, and we marvel at how far IF has come or note what the games did
right or how they failed.  Sometimes, with games like Jason Clayton White&#x27;s
House of the Stalker, we can&#x27;t help but wonder, what was the author smoking?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s rare that I include game text in a review (okay, I&#x27;ve just never done it
before), but with this game, I feel that I must:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Attic&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;You are in your attic, scared out of your wits. The killer may be down there waiting for you, or he may not know you&#x27;re there at all. Then there&#x27;s always the chance that it was your cat rustling on the kitchen table or something, in which case you would laugh and slap up the kitty a bit. There is something about this situation, though, that sets your heart racing.&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, death looms around every corner, but it&#x27;s not always at the hands
of a homicidal maniac with the fear-inspiring name of &amp;quot;Keith Alfonzo.&amp;quot;
Sometimes it&#x27;s in the form of a bowling ball to the head when one foolishly
opens up a closet door, releasing piles of junk.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We learn that the PC lives in an empty house (well, except for the cat) with
an empty heart, still saddened by the departure of his spouse and kids.
Fortunately, he has a mini-disc player that plays &amp;quot;Ride of the Valkyries&amp;quot;
deafeningly loud to help him forget his troubles.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When playing horror games, I always expect the killer to jump out in two
turns, at which point it&#x27;s all carefully timed &#x27;guess the verb&#x27; head-banging
frustration.  &#x27;House of the Stalker&#x27; only partly succumbs to this.  The killer
doesn&#x27;t appear until you go out of your way to find him, almost to the point
where you want to grab the PC and say, &amp;quot;dude, what are you freaking out
about?&amp;quot;  When you do eventually confront the killer, yeah, it becomes a
death fest.  I&#x27;m pretty sure (ok, I admit that I&#x27;m writing this review a year
or so after I last played the game) that I resorted to a walkthrough or text
dump.  Of course, the response to &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;KICK MAN (&amp;quot;Don&#x27;t go violent on the the killer!&amp;quot;)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is quite entertaining, but even more interesting is the way that
your character disarms and completely pacifies our friend Keith before killing
him.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I presume the remaining question is, is the game worth playing?  On one hand,
the execution leaves something to be desired.  The writing is sloppy (although
the style cracked me up) and the code, buggy.  I actually refrained from
including other bits of text because I didn&#x27;t want to spoil all of its &#x27;jokes&#x27;,
which aren&#x27;t as numerous as I recalled.  Still, as clichéd as games like these
are, they carry that spark of inspiration that most &#x27;this is my apartment&#x27; and
&#x27;treasure quest&#x27; games lack, and sometimes that&#x27;s enough to win a place in your
heart.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
</feed>
